<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christianity indeed, or, The well-disciplin'd Christian the delight of Christ shewing how believers in Christ ought to go in and out each before other in gospel-order, governing and being governed as the children of one Father / by Fr. Stanley.</title>
            <author>Stanley, Fr. (Francis), d. 1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 220 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5234</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16976870</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16976870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173115</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61284)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173115)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:44)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christianity indeed, or, The well-disciplin'd Christian the delight of Christ shewing how believers in Christ ought to go in and out each before other in gospel-order, governing and being governed as the children of one Father / by Fr. Stanley.</title>
                  <author>Stanley, Fr. (Francis), d. 1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 153, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1667?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: The Gospel's honour, and the churches ornament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church polity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173115:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173115:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſtianity indeed OR, <hi>The well-diſciplin'd Chriſtian the Delight of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SHEWING, How Believers in Chriſt ought to go in and out each before other in Goſpel-Order; Governing, and being Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as the children of one Father.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Fr. Stanley.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Phil. 4.8.</hi>
                  </bibl> Finally brethren, whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; If there be any vertue, and if there be any praiſe, think on theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Chap. 1.27.</hi>
                  </bibl> Onely let your Converſation be as it becometh the Goſpel of Christ, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle without <hi>Temple-bar.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173115:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173115:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt worthy my well beloved, and dear Relations in the Lord, of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Churches, both Officers and Members; whom I humbly crave to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronize this ſmall and mean Treatiſe, for whoſe ſake I chiefly formed it, and for whoſe benefit I now preſent it; For whom I can do no leſs but wiſh all increaſe of Grace, and fulneſs of Peace; and as a further Duty and Obligation, to pray and intercede for your Perfection.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Beloved and Chriſtian Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is the holy Scriptures commendation, That it's written for every Mans Inſtruction and as there is a myſtery of Godlineſs and Piety, ſo there is a myſtery of Sin and Iniquity; and as there are Mines of Heavenly Treaſure, ſo there are Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of Tin and Clay: Now Many are ſo wrapt in darkneſs in the depth of Impiety, and others buſied la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in the Earth for Clay, that they have not hitherto diſcovered the Celeſtial and hidden Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, nor found out the Spiritual Mines of Divine Treaſures; which precious things cannot be obtained, unleſs by Gods holy Spirit a Man be inſpired; for
<pb facs="tcp:173115:3"/>by Divine light a Man muſt come to diſcern ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting Mines and Myſteries, and by the eternal Spirit, which ſearcheth the hidden and moſt ſecret things; And as theſe are not Matters of Indifferency or Temporary, ſo they are to be ſought with more than ordinary diligence and induſtry; and for our better guidance, and more ſure direction, we muſt make uſe of the helps of Divine Inſpiration. I can do no leſſe but call upon all Chriſtian Profeſſors to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to the Canonical Books of the holy Scriptures; For among all other Benefits and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, we are to bleſs God for thoſe holy Writings; for they are the beſt helps, that are helps in the beſt things; And as a Mapp directs both to Town and Country, ſo doth holy Writ diſcover the Borders and Treaſures of the Heavenly and Holy City; indeed they are like a light to our feet, and a lanthorn to our paths, to guide us aright in all Gods pure and holy wayes, and to the finding out of the moſt choyce and invaluable Riches, far better to the Saints than Pearls and Jewels; for they are more than a Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for Inſtruction, like a Store-houſe for Soul-provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and like a Spiritual Armorie for Munition, where is to be found all manner of heavenly Food for Nutriment, and all kinde of holy Garments for Ornament; I may ſay, 'tis like an Apotheries ſhop for Receipts and Remedies, even the moſt ſoveraign helps againſt all in troubles and diſeaſes; ſuch Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals will make Potions for Soul-ſick Patients, which
<pb facs="tcp:173115:3"/>being skilfully compounded, and carefully applied, may prove effectual Means and powerfull Remedies to expel and drive away moſt dangerous Diſtempers. From hence Chriſtians may be directed and provided with Skill and right Judgement, and principled and furniſhed with Rules for all Order, Diſcipline and Government, whether it be within the Dominion of Congregational, Perſonal, or Family Juriſdiction. Beſides this, a Man may collect and form an Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in order to the claiming an Intereſt to the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Inheritance. To be be ſhort, here is all varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Soul-concernment and Contentment towards the fitting a Mans ſelf, clearing his Aſſurance for his Eternal Preferment; We may ſay of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in Reſolution, as once was ſaid in anſwer to Circumciſion, That they are profitable every way; even to ſuch as order their Lives according to them, have both the promiſe of this life, and that which is to come. Now as the Sun goes his courſe, and gives light in his place, and every Star in his order gives ſome light in his courſe: So ought every Chriſtian to be a light in his day, with reſpect to order and place; and as a Member of the Myſtical Body I would caſt a Mite into the Publick Treaſurie; and as one of the unworthy Succeſſors of our antient Fathers, who ſent their Epiſtles to the Believing Churches, I have now an Occaſion as well as a Pattern to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſomething to Chriſts Congregation: Or any Well-wiſhers who ſee any thing worth of acceptation,
<pb facs="tcp:173115:4"/>that may deſerve the place of Counſel or Direction, wherein they may ſee themſelves concerned in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ingaged in Duties to conform thereunto, according to Scripture-obligations: Now becauſe a Paper-direction may be received, where a Mans Perſon will be refuſed; and a Matter printed may be imbraced, where a Sermon cannot be preached; and becauſe the greateſt things have the ſmalleſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, and the Lord hath ordained ſtrength out of the mouth of Babes and Sucklings, are moving Cauſes of my entering upon this Work; and ſo I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this ſmall Labour to be peruſed and proved con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the prime Rules of Chriſtianity, and the pure Principles of Charity, and ſo to receive its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation or correction. Now if this little Mite be by any accepted and imbraced, if any by it be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and profited, the Author hath his End, and is well recompenced and ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Brethren, This is the firſt of my looking towards the Preſs, I hope I ſhall have an Allowance from you more or leſs, where I have failed in Method or Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, I hope you will blot it out of your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:173115:4"/>
            <head>THE Preface, or Premonition, preſented to the Readers ſerious Conſideration or Meditation.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian, Courteous, and Impartial Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS the worth and loſs of Heaven can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be imagined or valued, ſo the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and perpetuall torments of Hell can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be meaſured nor reported: To deſign the obtaining of the one, and to endeavour to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the other, is the great task and ſpeciall care of every Goſpell-profeſſor; and in order to theſe things, as it is the Chriſtian mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to ask counſell of God and his holy wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, ſo 'tis alſo his diſcretion to have an eye to his preſent diſpenſations.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.32</note> We have lived to be eye and ear-witneſſes to hear and behold Gods eminent hand, both in reſpect of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:173115:5"/>and mercies, wherein his fatherly care hath been famouſly and affectionately diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the ſoul-proviſions he hath made for us, and his princely reſpect hath been eminently demonſtrated, by the conſtant protection and ſpeciall ſecurity he hath given us; who hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo attended and alarmed us by loud calls, by happy inſtruments, miraculous mercies, and admoniſhed us by fearfull apparitions, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular accidents, and dreadfull judgements, all doubtleſs to provoke to duty, and that we might have a childs part in the preſent mercy, to eſcape the preſent ſeverity, to avoid the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture miſery, and to preſerve and conduct us to the haven of Eternity. The Lords princely fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and acts of indempuity and compaſſion, have been marvelouſly commended to us, in his great patience, long-ſuffering, and forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of us, yet preſerving our priviledges, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging our liberties, augmenting our graces, and that while others have fallen by calamities. Nay have not many cauſe, the whole term of their lives, to remember how eminently they have been preſerved from the ſword, peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and as brands pulled out of the fire. It becomes us as obedient Children, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us as loyall Subjects, to give ear and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſubmit to the Lords voice, whether by mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies or threatnings, warning or corrections.
<pb facs="tcp:173115:5"/>Chriſtian Reader, we are admoniſhed by this diſpenſation, to hear the rod of correction,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 3.6.</note> and to conſider who appoints it. Is there any evil in a City, and the Lord hath not done it; 'tis more than propheſied, for many have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready both known and felt what it is for a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God, to come down out of his place, and to ſhew his angry face in his hot diſpleaſure: For proof, let the Citizens eſpecially remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, who live in the Metropolitan City, whom I might call to witneſs if need did require, to tell their experience of Gods late Method in the peſtilence and fire; and if we needed any further teſtimony, to ask the Sea-men concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſword devouring in the Sea. It doth therefore properly and more than ordinarily concern every Chriſtian, to be ſtrict in attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſpeedy in obſervation, and ſtudy to learn what the Lord ſpeaks to us in this preſent diſpenſation, before the Lord pour out the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainder of his wrath upon the children of men. For among whom is there ſuch a reformation, that might give us juſt ground to believe, the righteous God will ſtay his hand of deſtroying; only he is long-ſuffering, ſurely to ſee what uſe will be made of the laſt Viſitation. Let us therefore ſtudy the point and ſtate the queſtion, what ſutable ſacrifice we ſhould prepare for,
<pb facs="tcp:173115:6"/>and preſent to the God of Heaven, that might be as fruit in its ſeaſon from us, and acceptably received and reſented by him; for certainly our treſpaſſes are aggravated, by not improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our mercies we have enjoyed.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs the abuſe of mercies is the door that lets in all our miſeries: There is therefore nothing more incumbent upon us, than thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to improve our bleſſings, and remove far from us that which procures Gods diſpleaſures, and to prize our unexpected and undeſerved fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and freedomes, and ſenſibly to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our precious immunities and benefits in the uſe of them, that we may never know their price and loſs in the want of them, for ſins commited againſt benefits received, and that in the midſt of calamities, which for ſeaſon and circumſtance are no leſs than miracles and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, which being not prized thankfully, we may expect ſeverity to take place in the room of mercy. For truly ſuch have been the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent appearances of God, the nature, number, and meaſure of our priviledges, who hath by his moſt admirable and remarkable acts of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and his more inviſible and ſecret way of providence, defended and ſecured his poor he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage, not only when the multitude have ſtood for us, but ſince they have turned their force againſt us: So that he that turned aſide as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:173115:6"/>may ſee a great ſight to be admired, to ſee as it were the Buſh to burn, and yet not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; ingratitude for ſuch experiences with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt will return in great ſeverities. Let us therefore conſult our knowledge, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collect our memories, caſt up accounts, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto the Lord his due, in returning praiſes, and chearfully acknowledge our debts, and ſpeedily pay our vows, that we may be counted worthy to be the Lords Tenants, that we may ſtill hold our benefits, and poſſeſs our privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges.</p>
            <p>For if in theſe things Chriſtians are found in neglects and ſecurity, they may expect to find the Lord in wrath and fury. For the Lord hath made our famous City, the beauty and glory of our Nation, to be as a Beacon to alarm the Countrey, and to give them warning: He might have made us preſidents of warning to others, but 'tis our priviledge to make others examples of warning to us. Let not us he like ſome who cry out of certain perſons, ſad acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and complain of bad times, and yet put the cauſe of all theſe things from themſelves, not pondering nor reflecting upon the matter, that 'tis our deſerts, we deſerve no better. There is no ſort or ſect of men the righteous God hath ſpared in this ſad Viſitation, then, which is the people that are to be exempted in
<pb facs="tcp:173115:7"/>the reformation. Now that our mercy may not be turned into miſeries, and our chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into judgements, Reader, let it be the next queſtion, what the Lord requires in duty to be done; the reſolution may be taken out of that ſhort Breviate of <hi>Micah</hi> the Prophet,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.9.</note> the ſumme of which duty conſiſts in juſtice, mercy, and humility; for this is to bear the rod, to do juſtly, to love mercy, and to walk humbly with God: For indeed this is the work of our day, and theſe are the weightier matters of Gods Law; and as Eccleſiaſticall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and true diſcipline is a prime part of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſo 'tis a proper work to purge Chriſts Congregation; and becauſe our holy God hath a quick and ſtrict eye upon his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and his jealouſie is hotteſt about the Altar, Ark, and Sanctuary, witneſs the ſeverity of his juſtice upon <hi>Nadah,</hi> and <hi>Abihu,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.2.</note> Corah, Uzzah,</hi> and <hi>Ely.</hi> Alſo remember the ſtate of the Church of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> which may be a Mapp and glaſs for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in theſe late times,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.32.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we may diſcover our miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours, the nature of our calamities, and a method for our remedies, who ſuffered becauſe the Church was not purged, and becauſe they
<pb facs="tcp:173115:7"/>preſumed to be Communicants at the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and did not diſcern the Lords Body, but came unworthily, and kept their Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons irreverently and diſorderly, inſomuch (for this cauſe) the Lord in flicts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, weakneſs, ſickneſs,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.30.</note> and mortality. So that it firſt and moſt concerns the Church of God to ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot this materiall duty, even the exerciſe of juſtice, mercy, and humility, and impartially to judge our ſelves, that we may not be judged of the Lord, nor condemned with the world, but haſten to put judgement into execution, to cleanſe our Camps, purge our Tabernacles, and Churches, both from our own and other mens ſins, both Nationall, Congregationall, Family, and Perſonall crimes; for true Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment hath this commendation, by its exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution it orders, purges, and eſtabliſhes Chriſts Congregation: Thus runs the duty of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, fervently to ſerve the Lord, applying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the time and occaſion. And further Chriſtian Reader, the righteous God hath not only admoniſhed us to do our duty, but hath given us a method by his late example, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt iniquity. 1. He counſells and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs by many inſtruments, much tenderneſs, and oft entreaties. 2. He doth admoniſh and wait to be gracious, and that with long-ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="tcp:173115:8"/>and much patience. 3. He warns, alarms by particular preſidents of his anger, ſad acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and threatens by fearfull ſights and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions. 4. If yet they reform not, he ſends as we ſee his rod and ſword, and cuts off many perſons, and makes great deſolations. Thus ſaith <hi>Micah</hi> the Prophet, <hi>The Lord hath ſhewed thee O man what is good,</hi> which being done with an eye to the preſent condition, might prove a ſoveraign means to prevent or remove future tribulation.</p>
            <p>But Chriſtian Reader, for my own part and partern, I look at the example of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Corinthian</hi>-Congregation; when he ſaw their diſorder and impiety, their affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and calamity, he magnifies his authority, and diſcharges his duty, obſerving the Lords own method; after counſell and warning he ſeems to threaten with his rod, and preſſes the Church to purge themſelves, by puniſhing evil doers, and reforming their abuſes: And leſt the Church ſhould queſtion their power and privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the execution of judgement and juſtice, he convinces them the Saints ſhall judge the world and Angels, much more then thoſe ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler matters, and that they ſhould judge upon life and death, much more things that pertain to this preſent life. And that he might put it out of all diſputation, he ſaith, ſet them to
<pb facs="tcp:173115:8"/>judge in the Church who are of the leaſt eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and further he ſaith, 'tis a ſhame for Chriſtians to go out of the Church to try their Cauſes; ſo that I have both an occaſion and a pattern to write thus to Chriſts Congregation. That which is moſt called for is right diſcipline, and that thing is the moſt of all wanting, by which our Borders and Churches ſhould be cleanſed of all defilements and pollutions. Theſe things conſidered; 1. May be forceable Arguments to induce Chriſtians to exerciſe a more ſearching doctrine, and to execute a more ſevere diſcipline, and that in every place and Congregation. 2. My obſervation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell-Churches: Some are careleſs in matters of doctrine; ſome faulty in caſes of converſation; but more generally remiſs in the true order of Governing. 3. Some looking upon Church-Government to be little leſs than tyranny, and their ſubmiſſion to it little leſs than ſlavery. 4. Others looking upon it, as if it had no name, being, or place, or as if it ſtood for no purpoſe and uſe. 5. Becauſe ſuch neglects and generall omiſſions, open a door to let in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſorders and diviſions. And becauſe I do not remember that any Friend hath writ much upon this Subject before, are the motives of my enlarging upon this Work. I confeſs this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject is too high and too worthy to be handled by
<pb facs="tcp:173115:9"/>one ſo unworthy, and of ſo mean ability; yet I would open a door to let ſome other in to view this Subject, even to lend their help to ſupply my defects, and make it more perfect; even one that hath faith in the honeſty of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and to cover my failings by a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſtruction. And ſo I commit it to the uſe of Edification, and alſo preſent it for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of Chriſts Congregation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173115:9"/>
            <head>A TREATISE, Setting forth <hi>The Goſpel's Honour,</hi> AND <hi>The Churches Ornament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN all Nations, Provinces, and in every Society, there are two principal Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Peace and common Proſperity, where Superiours freely exerciſe right Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Inferiours are truly ſubject, and obedient: Even when Vertue and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doers are ſutably praiſed, and conſtantly protected; and all Vice and evill-doers tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſtrained, and duly puniſhed: When the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173115:10"/>People are in reall ſubmiſſion to Authority and the Rulers in humble ſubmiſſion to the Power of thoſe Laws they ought to rule by: Even when Government is proſecuted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out knowing of Faces, and Juſtice executed without regard to Cauſes, or reſpects of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. And as the moſt High and Mighty God is the Worlds Creator, ſo Government is his Royall Act and Excellent Creature; and for it's Eminency, 'tis as antient as the World for Antiquity. For when the Lord had devided the Darkneſs from the Light, He made the Sun to rule by Day, and the Moon by Night: So when the Moſt Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord hath called and devided the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Light from the Children of this World, and Tranſlated them out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Darkneſſe into the Kingdome of his dear Son, and ſo they become his Spiritual Subjects, and He their Immortal King. Thus am I directed into my way, and caſt upon my deſigned Subject; which is my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Purpoſe and reſolved Intent, even to treat touching Chriſt's Princely Authority, and Eccleſiaſtical Government, which I call, <hi>The Goſpel's Honour,</hi> and, <hi>The Churches Ornament;</hi> And for my better proſecution of this Matter, I will obſerve this following Method and Order.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:173115:10"/>
               <item>1. To ſhew the Antiquity and Dignity of Eccleſiaſtical Government.</item>
               <item>2. The Definition, The ſeveral Parts and particular Acts of it.</item>
               <item>3. The ſeveral Reaſons for it, and great Neceſſity of it.</item>
               <item>4. Declaring the Uſe and great Benefit that comes by it.</item>
               <item>5. Some Rules tendred, directing how to Effect and Accompliſh it.</item>
               <item>6. The true Order and right Manner of the Execution of it.</item>
               <item>7. And Laſtly, Some Directions given, how to uphold and ſupport it.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>1. Of the Firſt; <hi>Touching the Antiquity and Dignity of Eccleſiaſtical Government.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Excellency, Antiquity, and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of all Power and Authority con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon the Goſpel-Church, deſcends from the Chriſt of God, who is the Original Author, and from whom it receives it's prime Honour. We may ſay in this caſe as 'tis ſaid by the Wiſe Man, <hi>For what can the man do that cometh after the King? Even that which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173115:11"/>hath been already done;</hi> who now under the New Teſtament is the only Law-giver, and chief Eſtabliſher of Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: all Power in Heaven and Earth is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, and all Juſtice and Judgement is committed to him, and all ſubordinate Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is derived from him; His Perſonal Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies and Princely Vertues are not to be compared but admired. I have not words to expreſſe his Royall Majeſty, and to ſet forth his Excellent Glory: He is exalted far above all Principalities, and far ſurpaſſeth all Names and Dignities; for the God-Head dwels in him bodily, and he is more than worthy of all Duty and Glory; His Love unparalel'd, his Wiſdome matchleſs, his Power boundleſſe, his Juſtice unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, his Innocency admirable, his Treaſures ineſtimable, his Fidelity inexpreſſable, <hi>Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel,</hi> God with us, and who is Exalted above, and triumphs over all his Enemies. The moſt High and Mighty Prince, upon whom he fals he grinds to powder, and cruſhes his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries by his Power, and breaks them in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces like Potters veſſels; who acted ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently for the Glory of the Creator, and ſo happily for the happineſſe of the Creature, that Divine Juſtice might be compleatly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and Mercy towards man admirably
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:173115:11"/>advanced: He that thought it no Robbery to be equal with God, hath freely humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to death, to drink of a bitter Cup, and to bear the Creatures burdens; Even he ſhall have the Government upon his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
               <p>The Glory that attends him, further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by thoſe <hi>Excellent Appellations attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him: His Name ſhall be called the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull Counſellor, the Mighty God, the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Father, the Prince of Peace, by whom Princes Reign, and Judges decree fuſtice:</hi> who upholds all things by the word of his Power, and is able to deſtroy all things in his wrath and anger: He is the great Judge of quick and dead, both of this New and the Old World; and ſhall pronounce the laſt and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Sentence of the everlaſting Abſolution and eternal Condemnation, and that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to every mans known and ſecret acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; who hath overcome the World and the power of the Devill; having the victory, keeps the Keys of Death and Hell; who is all-ſufficient to protect and ſecure ſuch as worſhip him, and to reſtrain and deſtroy ſuch as fight againſt him; from Sea to Sea is his Dominion; the utmoſt parts of the Earth is his poſſeſſion. The abſolute Soveraign of all Nations, the Univerſal Governour over
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173115:12"/>all Perſons and Countries; he is the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega;</hi> all people are commanded and bound to honour him; every knee ſhall bow, and every tongue confeſſe him; his Laws are Spiritual, Righteous and Mercifull; all his requirements are perfect and pure; and all his promiſes are ſecurity, certain and ſure. This is the Immortal King of Saints, who in his times will ſhew who is the bleſſed and only Potentate King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; I ſay he is the chiefeſt among Ten Thouſands: Firſt, In reſpect of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Beauty, for he is altogether lovely. Secondly, In reſpect of Purity, without ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blemiſh or ſpot of Iniquity. Thirdly, In reſpect of Charity, caſting his love upon a loſt World found in Impurity. Fourthly, In reſpect of Policy, who knows the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Conſpiracy, and catcheth the wiſe in their own ſubtilty. Fifthly, In reſpect of Propriety, who makes many Poor Rich out of his full Treaſury. Sixthly, In reſpect of Soveraignty, who in the moſt eminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers can hide and keep ſecurely. Seventh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, In reſpect of Perpetuity, who can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow Rewards of never ending Glory. The ſame is head over all things to his Church, and Lord over all to the Conſcience. We muſt all appear before him, be judged
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173115:12"/>by him, and every one muſt give an account of himſelf to him: he only can preſcribe Rules for the Soul and Conſcience; who gives life and grace, and none but he can take it away; who keeps the keys of theſe privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and opens and no man ſhuts, and ſhuts and no man opens. He only knows the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affections, the omiſſions and ſubmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the heart to his Requirements. Heart-Iniquity is out of mans view to take notice, and out of the reach of mortal man to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh. The Lord only can reward with ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Preferment, and none but he can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict eternal puniſhment. This is the Saints great Prophet, High Prieſt, and Eternal King, who hath of his own free will and donation bequeathed a ſubordinate power to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Congregation; committing to them a great truſt, and conferring upon them a great honour; ſaying, <hi>Whatſoever ye bind on Earth ſhall be bound in Heaven, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye looſe on Earth ſhall be looſed in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; Whoſe ſins ye remit ſhall be remitted, and whoſe ſins ye retain ſhall be retained:</hi> and as a further Demonſtration of dignifying them, he hath been pleaſed to impart ſome of his Communicable Titles to them; and that they of his Elderſhip (in his abſence) ſhould ſerve under him, and act for him, in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173115:13"/>the Offices of Prophet, Prieſt and King, in a far inferiour and ſubordinate ſence and low degree; acting by his Authority, and yet with an humble reſpect and great humility in his ſervice; who ought to be honourably attended with all holy obedience, in all hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs, and with all due Reverence and Thankfulneſſe: Repreſenting his Perſon, Acting all in his Name, by vertue of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Commiſſion committed to them. Thus he lends them his Names, ſets them in his Room, gives them the keys of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, puts his Image upon them, and hath committed the charge of his People, the care of his Laws, and the exerciſe of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to them; and when the laſt day Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be called, the Saints ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned as Jurors, upon Life and Death, to judge the World. And as Prayer and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holds forth his Prophetical and Prieſtly Office, ſo right Government holds forth his Princely Office and Dignity of his Place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:173115:13"/>
               <head>2. <hi>True Church Government defined, and the ſeveral Parts and particular Acts distinguiſhed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw right Church Government under the Power of Chriſt, according to the Rules of the New Teſtament, inflicts no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily puniſhment; but is a juſt exerciſing and due executing of all his Righteous and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Laws in being; conſonant to his Council and direction given, without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Intereſt, delay of Juſtice, reſpect to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, wreſting Cauſes either for favor or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to any degree of perſons; for we have but one Law for the ſame Offence, which knows no face, nor regards no Circumſtance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Church Government conſiſts of theſe ſeveral parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Governours, Inferiours, Laws, and Execution. Or thus, A People truly called, and rightly gathered, Officers fitly qualifi'd, and orderly Ordained, Chriſt's Laws exactly minded, and carefully preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, every man's Cauſe timely heard, and Juſtice duly executed. The true conſtitution and right governing of Chriſt's Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may be further inlarged and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thus: 1. Where the People are really
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173115:14"/>converted. 2. Where they are legally and wholly ſeparated. 3. Who for Truths ſake ſuffer, if perſecuted. 4. Where the Word is truly preached. 5. Where the People are truly formed, and Duties orderly obſerved. 6. Where the Ordinances and Sacraments are purely adminiſtred. 7. And true Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline duly ordered.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The more particular Acts of Eccleſiaſtical Government, according to the Primitive pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern, and Chriſt's appointment, is, That the Miniſter or Governour is ingaged and ſtands obliged to watch over each Member in love; duely inſtructing them, going before them, praying for them, to be an example to them, in Word, in Converſation, in Charity, in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, in Faith &amp; Purity; To teach the Ignorant, to ſtrengthen the Weak, to comfort the Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble minded, ſuccour the Tempted, incourage the Faint-hearted, reſtore the Fallen, admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the Negligent, viſit the Sick, defend them from Deceivers, ſeek up the Wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and Strayers, reprove idle and buſie bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, warn the Unruly, correct Tale-bearers and Back-biters, ſharply reprove Diſturbers and Diviſion-makers, openly rebuke publick Offenders, imbrace penitent Perſons, reject Hereticks, exclude Contemners and obſtinate Perſons, abſolve the truly humbled Treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173115:14"/>hear the Cauſes of Complainers, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Witneſſes, hear the defence of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants, reſpecting the Poor mans Cauſe as well as the Rich, admoniſhing with compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, re-admoniſhing and reproving with Long-ſuffering and Doctrine, waiting with patience the reſtoring offenders. Not to keep company, but refuſe to aſſociate with ſuch perſons which are Excommunicate, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes obſerving the Tempers of Perſons, the nature of Offences, and ſeaſonable times; ſome ſave with fear, and ſome with compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſome with ſoftneſſe, and others with ſharpneſſe; let all be done in Juſtice and Charity, without demurs, delays, or partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; let all be done freely and in order, without exerciſing Lordſhip, or having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Lucre; but to adde to their perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of duty themſelves patterns of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Humility and Piety. Thus I have ſhewed in part what that Ancient, Spiritual, Apoſtolical Government is: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rightly ordered, and truely executed, will anſwer to my firſt Intent, and amount to the aforeſard Account; even to hold forth Chriſt's Glory, <hi>the Goſpel's Honour, and the Churches Ornament.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:173115:15"/>
               <head>3. <hi>The Reaſons for, and neceſſity of Church Governors and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. BEcauſe Chriſt's Congregation is a Spiritual Common-wealth, and holy Nation; where Spiritual Traffique is free,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> where Gifts, Graces, and Priviledges are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. It conſiſts of Spiritual Fathers, Children, Young men, and ſtrong men, and hath many Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, much Treaſures, and many Enemies. Now Order and Government is the ſtrength of a Nation, and as walls to a City, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve heavenly Treaſure from the Spiritual Enemy: all which beſpeak the need the Church hath of Officers and Governors; for indeed what is a Church, Family, or Nation, without Government, but diſorder and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. If the glorious Sun ſhould retire his light, and ſtay his courſe, and the Moon and Stars forbear their ſhining in the way of their Circuit and place, which the Lord hath appointed Rulers over day and night, Times and Seaſons, Light and Darkneſſe would fall together; then all would be in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173115:15"/>confuſed mixture. So in truth take away Governours and Government from the Church of Chriſt, and ye take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Prop and Pillar of this Spiritual Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and lay aſide it's Inſtrumental Defence and Security; and ſo lay it open to be taken and carried Captive by the Spiritual Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. In all which appears the Reaſon and Neceſſity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Church of Chriſt is an Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Court, or Spiritual Chancery, where all proceedings are to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the prime Rules of Juſtice,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.2. and 10.</note> and pure Principles of Equity and Charity: where all offences and injuries com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and all Offices, and Duties neglected are to be examined and determined, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that ancient Law, <hi>Of doing as man would be done by.</hi> Now how can Matters in a Court be Regulated and Executed without Orders and Officers: Therefore our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord hath Commiſſionated his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to be as Judgers and Stewards, impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered by him, to Act for him in his ſtead and abſence, to hold forth the Majeſty of his Preſence, by Perſonating him, Repreſenting his Authority, and holding forth his Glory, in reſpect of Dignity, Mercy, Purity and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173115:16"/>Severity, preciſely to look to his Rights and Priviledges, Dues and Duties, and to inflict due puniſhments upon all Offenders, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Offences; To have an eye to his Spiritual Rolls, and Holy Writings; and in the exerciſe of Government, to produce Commiſſions from the Lord, and give ſome charge, according as Gods Spirit hath given charge in the Word: and ſo all things to be done juſtly without partiality.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Chriſt's Church is a Church Militant, and muſt manage a Warfare with the Prince of this World, the Old Serpent, who is the moſt grand Politician,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.18. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.11, 13.</note> and cruell Enemy; whoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is chiefly againſt the Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Generation, and Holy City; who joyns in league with the World, the luſts of the fleſh, and all wicked Inſtruments, &amp; is furniſhed with fiery darts, ſtrong ſnares, ſubtill wiles, and ſecret policy, to invade the borders, and betray the ſouls of ſuch as profeſſe Chriſtianity, indeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to divide them from the Armour and Weapons of the Word, and to diſarm them of their defence by the ſpiritual ſword; ſometimes in fury ſtorming the Caſtle of our bodies, to rob us of the Treaſure of our ſouls: even to ſteal away our ſpiritual Evidence,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173115:16"/>to deprive us of our everlaſting Inheritance. Is not here Reaſon enough to ſhew the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of being provided with all Spirituall Artillery, and to exerciſe all Chriſtian poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to put our ſelves into beſt Poſtures, and holy Orders; furniſhed with all Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and the exacteſt Diſcipline and Formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with courage and conſtancy to maintain the cauſe of Religion and Piety, with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and ſobriety, and with great watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and fidelity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Church of God is fitly compared to a Vineyard, which is to be ſeparated from other ground,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</note> which is to be choiſely Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, timely Watered, duly Pruned, and well Fenced. Now Chriſt's Miniſters are Planters, Waterers and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and Government is as the Fence to the Churches. It's good to ſee the Vine when it flouriſhes; but let it alone, and in a ſhort time it will ruine it ſelf by ſuperfluous Branches: Even ſo for want of Spiritual Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſers, Decays and Ruines ſuddenly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall flouriſhing Churches. The Lord hath therefore appointed Labourers in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, to dreſſe it and ſecure it. This ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude teacheth us that things will ſoon be at a loſs in Chriſt's Vineyard, unleſs there be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173115:17"/>ſome Governour to over-ſee it, order and preſerve it; which ſhewes the Reaſon for it, and Neceſſity of it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The People of God are compared to a Flock of Sheep, and Lambs; and wicked men to Foxes, and devouring Wolves. Now Chriſtians are too much like ſheep,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28, 29. <hi>Joh.</hi> 21.15.16.</note> in reſpect of careleſs feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and without fear of devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; ſheep will feed in ſuch unwholſome Paſtures without guides, that inſtead of feeding, they infect themſelves, to the loſs of their lives; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides where there is no Shepheard to lead and defend them, then comes the Wolves and Foxes and ſcatters and worries them. We may ſay by ſad experience we have known the ſame among Chriſtians: all which Conditions and Expreſſions manifeſt clearly there is a Neceſſity of Paſtors and Shepherds in Chriſt's Congregation, to watch over them, feed them, govern them, and defend them from all ſuch deſtructive Creatures as ſeek to devour them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Becauſe the Saints are fitly compared to Merchant-men, and the Voyage of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity to a Ship paſſing through the Sea;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.45.</note> their Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick and Merchandice is the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173115:17"/>Treaſures of Knowledge, Gifts and Graces;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.19. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51.20.</note> Themſelves are like Merchant-Venturers; the Wicked like the troubled-Sea; the Saints hope, an Anchor; the broken in Faith, to Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack. Now how ſhould the Ships be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Seas without Pilats and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, becauſe of the force of Storms and Tempeſt, the violence of the Waves, and roughneſſe of the Waters, and the great difficulty of getting to Harbours. Now a good Miniſter and Governour is like a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Pilot, that takes the ſhorteſt and ſafeſt Courſe; who foreſees Dangers, and ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders his Affairs, that Rocks may be avoided, and Shipwrack prevented, all Pirats defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the Ship and her Treaſure ſecured. This alſo adds and confirms, that the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Concerns of a Church, had need to be well Manned, and to have skilfull men ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and to have all things well ordered and governed, having all means of ſafety that can be had, and all Inſtrumental helps that may be afforded.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That a Congregation of Chriſtians may be compared to ſo many Patients,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.21, 22.</note> who are always liable to ſpiritual diſeaſes, to be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173115:18"/>taken with ſeveral Diſtempers, and to fal into divers Temptations,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12, 13.</note> &amp; ſometimes into deſperate Conſumptive diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, either Luke-warmneſſe, Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Remiſneſs, Unfruitfulneſs, or unthankfulneſs, and the like; and are alſo ſubject to be infected with the Contagious Plague of ſin, and to be corrupted with the leaven of unſound Doctrine. Now Chriſt's Miniſters are or ought to be like good Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians, Firſt to know the Nature of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient's diſtemper, then ſort and prepare the Medicines, and ſo apply the means, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Tempers, Capacities, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of the Patients; and to give ſutable Receits for all Diſeaſes, for preventing, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; to give Potions and Cordials for Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, Preſerving and Comforting them; and for want of Skilfulneſs and Faithfulneſſe in Soul-Phyſitians, ſo many poor Chriſtian Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents fall into dangerous Relapſes and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Conſumptions; and for want of good Diſcipline and carefull Governours, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Societies run into ſuch ſad Diviſions and great Diſorders. Thus I have offered theſe ſeveral particulars in Argument, to manifeſt the Reaſons for, and the Neceſſity of Church Government.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:173115:18"/>
               <head>4. <hi>The good uſe and great benefit that comes by Right Government.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. IT is or ought to be the Firſt and Prime Deſign of every Chriſtian Profeſſor to contrive and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult the advancement of Chriſts Honour, which way,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.33. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.18.</note> and by what means they may beſt and moſt exalt the Dignity, and hold forth the Excellency of his Name, and by what Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental helps they may Principally Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his Princely Fame, in other Duties we perform to him; but in Matters of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Diſcipline, we more properly Act for him, Repreſent him, and help him, and bring home the moſt Praiſe and Glory to him. For we can in nothing more promote his Honour, then in the true execution of Government among ſuch as profeſſe the Goſpell. It returns the Lord increaſe of Glory, and renders him his own with Uſury. It encourages and praiſes Well-doers to be more Zealous and Fruitfull in their Actual Obedience, and it puniſhes Evill-doers: and ſo the Lord reaps the Honour of his Juſtice; and by this way and means the Lord will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:173115:19"/>receive his Honour from all Perſons, Actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by the godly Profeſſor, and Paſſively by evill Tranſgreſſor. And this is to rule for God, being always conſonant to the Rule and Circumſtance of his Word.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As the true Exerciſe of Eccleſiaſtical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is Chriſt's advancement; ſo 'tis <hi>The Goſpels Honour,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.10. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.45.</note> &amp; the Churches Ornament.</hi> It requires all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to their duties in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral and reſpective places, and admoniſhes all Chriſtians to a more Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Reverent, and Serious Deportment in Gods holy Worſhip and Service. It ſets all things in their right places, and puts all things to their proper uſes, to be done Decently and in Order, according to the true manner and direct Methods of Matter, Form and Circumſtance required in Gods Service: and things thus performed in Chriſts Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, promotes the Truths Credit, and the Believers Reputation; and having their own true form, they carry a Beauty with them: and like the order in <hi>Solomon's</hi> Houſe, it will invite ſtrangers to ſee it, and affect ſuch as behold it. One Argument is, why many inquiring ſouls ſtand off at ſuch diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Becauſe they ſee no affecting beauty in Chriſts Churches.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:173115:19"/> 3. As Right Government caſts out Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and diſorderly walkers, ſo it rejoyceth godly Profeſſors,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.5.</note> and preſerves Believers Rights and Priviledges, and miniſters juſt ground of joy, more eſpecially to ſuch as labour in the Miniſtry, to behold the peoples order and fidelity; and as a grave and holy life credits the Chriſtian Profeſſion, ſo true Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline honours the Goſpel-Doctrine; and the conſtant Exerciſe thereof is of ſuch emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent tendency, that good people rejoyce when Juſt men are in Authority:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 29.2.</note> For a Rulers Inſufficiency proves the Nocents Incouragement, and the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents calamity. For St. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Renowned in the Churches ſtedfaſt and orderly walkings; he rejoyces to behold it in the <hi>Colloſſians,</hi> and takes occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it, and to praiſe them for it; and counts it his Joy, Honour, and Crown.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Order and Right Governing ſtands in direct oppoſition to all diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and confuſion.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33.</note> 'Tis like Light oppoſed to Darkneſſe, Strength oppoſed to Weakneſs, Beauty oppoſed to Deformity. It reforms Diſorders, and orders Duties; It exalts any People, and eſtabliſhes Churches, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173115:20"/>ſtands as it were always furniſht and ready armed againſt the body of Sin and the deeds of the Old man: even the deſtructive enemy that would diſturb the Saints peace, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave their ſouls in miſery: It's natural to Juſtice to oppoſe and ſuppreſs Impiety:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7.</note> and 'tis it's proper work to praiſe Godlineſſe and diſperſe iniquity; It cleanſes Tabernacles, it purges Congregations, preſerves Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, removes Reproaches, it juſtifies the Innocent, it condemns the Guilty, it cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects the Offender, and puniſhes the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor, relieves the Diſtreſſed, and ſets free the oppreſſed, and is a ſoveraign Remedy to acquit our ſelves of other mens Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As the exerciſe of Government is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to iniquity and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</note> ſo it is a Protection to Godlineſſe and Piety; It gives opportunity and liberty for the free exerciſe of Gifts and Graces, and the improvement of ſpiritual Abilities,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.31.</note> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains a conſtant Entercourſe of Heavenly Traffick &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce within the Borders of their Dominion;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10.</note> to the intent things may thrive and flouriſh within the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173115:20"/>Holy Nation. Government is a defence to tender Plants in Chriſts Congregation: It gives countenance and a guarding preſence to the Seeds and Roots of Grace and Piety; and gives protection to the increaſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and defence and ſecurity to the growth of Chriſtianity. Therefore the Lord hath honored his Miniſters with ſome of his own Appellations, that they ſhould imitate and honour him in their ſeveral Offices and reſpective places; that they ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour under him to preſerve his People in all their freedomes and liberties, and to demean themſelves in his abſence with all tenderneſs and kindneſſe to the leaſt of his Servants: Not quenching the ſmoaking Flax, nor breaking the bruiſed Reed, but cheriſhing and nouriſhing the Babes in Chriſt; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Guard to every weak faith, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes free to direct them, and a ready aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in all matters of Faith and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p n="6">6. I ſay 'tis weighty upon the Churches Concernment to maintain good Order, true Diſcipline,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 8, 9, 10, 11.</note> and Right Government. It is the moſt effectual means and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign help (under God) againſt the grand Enemy of our Souls, who hath fiery darts
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173115:21"/>and makes deſperate Attempts, and ſets his Ambuſhments, and with policy and cruelty deſigns againſt the Saints to betray them by ſecret inſinuation, or to fright them out of their Faith and Profeſſion, and to weaken their hands for Chriſtian Reſolution; to break their bands of Union and Charity, and to cut the cords of Love and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.19.</note> endeavouring to diſorder them by ſowing Diſcord among them. Firſt, to divide them, to make way for an advantage to deſtroy them. Now Order is the Life and Strength of any Cauſe, and the moſt advantage to any People: for when a People are freely united and well Diſciplined, it is the greateſt offence and dread to the enemy; So 'tis when Chriſtians have faith in Gods promiſes, and keep order in his Services, it tends to their ſafety and ſecurity. When the Souldiers are diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Victory is hazarded; and he's no good Chriſtian-ſouldier that obſerves not Place and Order.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Right Government, which conſiſt Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally in the execution of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Judgement,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.7.</note> It may have the ſame commendation as was once given to Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion; for 'tis uſefull and beneficial every
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173115:21"/>way; and when Perſons ſhall ſee it in it's Beauty, and how it brings in profit, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves being partakers of the benefit of it. It will ingage and oblige the hearts of thoſe that live under it, peaceably and chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conform themſelves to it, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to approve of it, but in their ſeveral Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Reſpective Places with Freedome and Affection help to preſerve and ſupport it. For God himſelf is the Author of it, the Holy Ghoſt appoints overſeer of it, God dwels with it, and will certainly bleſſe it: for in truth Order duly kept, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment truly ordered, is of that Fame &amp; Glory it would invite ſtrangers out of the Country; As once the Order and Fame of <hi>Solomon's</hi> Houſe, invited the Queen of <hi>Sheba.</hi> If our Spiritual <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Houſe were but wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly governed, and the things therein rightly ordered, and all Matters and Mannors pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently managed, and all Diſcipline truly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, Strangers would be more invited, diſſenting friends and differing perſwaſions would be more ingaged, and Chriſts Church more Renowned. Thus I have ſhewed in part the benefit that comes to Chriſt's Church by means of Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:173115:22"/>
               <head>5. <hi>Some Rules tendred how to Effect and Accompliſh a right Government.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Firſt thing that I ſhall propound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, in order to this great end is, Their choiſe of Officers; and herein to beſpeak and exhort them that they neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect not their duty and care, and ſo the blame to lye at their door. None of the Saints and Brotherhood ought to conſult for private Intereſt, but for a general and publick good; that whoſoever among them the Lord hath ſuitably gifted, and fitly qualifi'd for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of ſinners, the conſtituting of Churches, and the well being, and better governing of Chriſt's Congregations; they ſtand bound in duty legally to elect and orderly to appoint ſuch to the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 13.3.</note> even to Separate and Ordain them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ſeveral Parts and Abilities to more general and particular places, even to follow the Lord, to put them into ſuch places as he hath gifted for that purpoſe: Even ſuch who come orderly into, and are tutered and brought up in the School of Chriſts Church, and learning there, untill
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173115:22"/>they come to good degrees of Knowledge; rightly qualified and conſiderably gifted by Gods Spirit: amongſt ſuch ſome are to be freely Elected by the Church, and Ordained by Faſting and Prayer, and laying on of hands by the Elderſhip; ſuch ſo Ordained and abiding Faithful we own as Miniſters of the Goſpell; and let them firſt be proved whether they have ſuch qualifications as the holy Scriptures gives directions. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a principall caſe towards the obtaining right Government; Take therefore advice of both old and New Teſtament; ye may pleaſe ſo far to view <hi>Moſes</hi> Counſel in the Old Teſtament, as to ſee what kind of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons was then choſen to be Rulers; Provide, ſaith he, <hi>Wiſe men, Underſtanding men, and known men in your Tribes; Men of courage, men fearing God, men of truth and hating Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteouſneſs:</hi> I offer this of <hi>Moſes,</hi> not ſo much for Rule, as for the good agreement it bears with the Rules of the New Teſtament. But give heed to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Counſell in the general qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications mentioned &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded for our directions;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. &amp;c.</note> which the Apoſtle ſets down both Negative and affirmative. Firſt, What they muſt not be; <hi>Not ſoon angry, not given to Wine, no
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173115:23"/>ſtriker; not ſelf-willed, not a brawler, not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, not a Novice.</hi> Secondly, What they muſt be; <hi>Blameleſſe, one that rules well his own houſe, apt to teach, a lover of good men, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, juſt, temperate,</hi> holding faſt the faithfull Word as he hath been taught; that they may improve and convince Gain-ſayers; and if it can be obtained, let them have the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Order, and ſpirit of Government, in and about this great Office and Duty. We are to look at a mans perſonal ſufficiency, the Gravity of his Yoke-fellow, the Fidelity of his Poſterity, and alſo the good report of his Neighbour-hood and Country. For if we would have Church-Government rightly ordered, there muſt be ſuitable Governours and fit Inſtruments to accompliſh it.</p>
               <p>Theſe Rules that follow, touching this point, are chiefly impoſed upon the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</p>
               <div type="rules">
                  <head>By <hi>Election, Direction, Protection, Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> and <hi>Excluſion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="2">2. By <hi>Election;</hi> As there is a great charge lies upon Churches, concerning the Election of Officers,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8.</note> So there is a ſpecial care lies upon Officers, touching the receiving and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173115:23"/>Members into the Congregation. To ſee ſome Fruits of Repentance, Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on renewed in the ſpirit of the mind, born a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; for ye know Churches under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell are not gathered by Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but by Regeneration,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.3.5, 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Except a man be born again, he cannot enter into the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi> For if they have not the birth of New Creatures, how can we expect the life of well ordered Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.</note> that they ſhould naturally learn the true Doctrine, and really obſerve, and duly ſubmit to the true methods of Diſcipline, which ſo much concerns and adorneth every Goſpel Congregation. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one had need underſtand Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and their own Duties, and to be able to demonſtrate ſomething of the authority, Matter, Manner, and End of every Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and practice; For Ignorance is the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of much miſchief; for ſome by their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviours diſcover and alſo their Actions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, that they never paſt the new birth. Neither is their deſcent from Heaven; for they act and walk as not becoming the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Family, and ſuch as pertain to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Poſterity; For many act ſo unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral towards the Lord, as if he was never
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:173115:24"/>their Father, and ſo untaught in his word and Oracles, that they are no whit like his Diſciples and Scholars; neither reſpecting Principles nor Orders, and ſome are already departed; being never well grounded, nor really and truly converted.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By <hi>Direction;</hi> By a due and ſeaſonable inſtructing and directing ſuch as are admitted into Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note> to acquaint and educate them in the knowledge of God, and the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Goſpel; &amp; to learn them to know the Principles of Order &amp; true Forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which are to be exercis'd under the New Teſtament: to keep cloſe to the direct Rules of Diſcipline, and right orders of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning, and to beget in them a Reſpect and Honour to the Truth, with all it's Oracles, and it's due Circumſtances, and to ſecond and ſeal this with a holy and well ordered, and a right governed Converſation; admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing them to obſerve the true Methods of proceedings towards all differing, diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, weak, faln, and offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Brerhren:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15.</note> To admoniſh the offending Brother timely before ſin hath hardened him. Secondly, If it be a private Offence, to tell him of it privately between thee and him alone, which
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:173115:24"/>is the ready way to gain him. Thirdly, To do it in Charity, wherein a man moſt reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles the God of Piety. Fourthly, the end muſt be to reſtore the ſinner, but to deſtroy his iniquity; alwayes remembring them to perform duty that relates to each other, with Compaſſion and Piety, as children of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Mercy; Even conſonant to their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Parentage &amp; Spiritual Pedegree, of the Select number, choſen Generation, Royall Prieſt hood, peculiar People &amp; holy Nation; like men of the new Creation, &amp; ſuch as are redeem'd from a vain Converſation; being as dead men to ſin, &amp; buried with Chriſt in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, &amp; riſen with him to Newneſs of life, &amp; ſo to exerciſe a ſpiritual Dominion, and give no place or ſubjection unto Sathan; but to endeavor to raign over the body of fleſh and ſin. But alas how oft is this general and known Rule abuſed and broken, wanting Charity to the perſon offending, or Fidelity to the Rule directing. The truth is, much of the Churches grief and care, breaks in among them at this door; but let Chriſts Miniſters lead and guide the Members into Rules of Piety, and Orders of Decency, and to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond their Exhortation by going before them as a pattern, and by good Counſel and by good Example to eſtabliſh the Believers
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173115:25"/>in Doctrine Diſcipline, and other Goſpell orders.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. By impartial Admonition and due Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; for as the Scripture ſaith in another caſe, in a Church-ſence, we may ſay in this, that Chriſt's Rulers bear not the ſpiritual ſword in vain, but to turn the edge of the Word againſt all vice &amp; iniquity,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12.</note> and to be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to all acts of Vertue and Piety; waiting all approaches, &amp; watching all deſigns of Sathan, and all motions and appearances of the fleſh. For many times the greateſt diſturbances are brought about by the leaſt beginnings: for 'tis Sathans policy to carry on his deſigns by entring them in by the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt appearances.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.20.</note> Beware there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of the works of the Fleſh, as Hatred, Variance, Emulation, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, Hereſies, and the like, which war againſt the Soul; which actings cauſe breaches and diſorders: unto which, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Over-ſeers are to have a fore-ſight of preventing, and a ready hand of ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch things as diſturb the peace of the Churches, and break orders; without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to Cauſes, or reſpect to Perſon, by a diligent and ſevere hand againſt all Tale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearers,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173115:25"/>Evill ſurmiſers, Back-biters, Rule-breakers, Deviſion-makers, ſecret Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers, and private Judges of others, who in their Court of Confuſion condemn their Brethren, and caſt them upon their Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Theſe and ſuch like are all Diſquieters of Churches, Wounders and Underminers of Governments; and for the better diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and removing all-ſuch diſturbances, let all diligence be exerciſed, all Circumſtances of Reprehenſion and Correction, be truly obſerved, and all ſuch offenders timely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained and duly puniſhed.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. By Countenancing and Protecting good orders, and giving incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to orderly Walkers.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 15.4.</note> To look with a ſowre face up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on evill doers, and a ſevere countenance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Evill workers; but to honour the Pious and to praiſe the truly Religious, to cheriſh them in their Duties, and incourage them in Gods ſervices. Now Goſpel-order is not only Beautiful and Honourable, but acceptable to God and profitable to men: for the Lord himſelf is Author of it, and his Peoples experience prove the great benefit by it. Let the Lords Overſeers approve themſelves prevalent inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to effect and keep
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:173115:26"/>good Government, &amp; by good Exhortation and Provocation ſtudy to maintain good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. For the Lord ſtrictly charges &amp; preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enjoyns Order in all his Services and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, Typical and Ceremonial, more eſpecially then in the Worſhip and Service of the Goſpel; where Duties are more rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bleſſed, and Defaults more ſorely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Let Rulers know their places and do their Offices, even cheriſh good people, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote good Cauſes, to aſſiſt good Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to endeavour to preſerve Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ansin their Liberties and Priviledges, ſuitng and ſorting their Counſels and Inſtructions, obſerving and taking advantages of ſeaſons, and the Peoples conditions; improving all abilities, and the beſt faculties to defend them from deceivers; giving timely admonition to Church-diſturbers. Succour the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, incourage the Faint-hearted, to take off yoaks and remove oppreſſions that may lye upon mens conſciences, watching diligently over them, carefully to govern them, gently leading ſuch as be with young, to keep them from decaying, to ſupport them from fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to reſtore them from erring, and like good Shepherds to feed and rule them, to defend and ſecure them from all thoſe Poxes and Wolves that ſeek to ſcatter them,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:173115:26"/>and endeavour to deſtroy them.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. By ſincere and fervent Supplication and Prayer, becauſe all things are ſanctified by the Word and Prayer; a duty never out of date,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Phi.</hi> 4.6. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17.</note> but in ſeaſon, and more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially upon ſuch weighty Concernments and eminent occaſions: as the elections of Officers, the admiſſion of Members, and in the great du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Direction, Correction, Protection and Excluſion. To acknowledge Gods grace to be the efficient Cauſe in all ſuch Matters, and to beg his Bleſſing upon all endeavours, without which all labour is nothing: pray to be directed aright to uſe the means, and then pray that the means may be ſanctified, may be ſucceſſeful and effectual, praying and waiting upon the great Counſellor, the prime Director, and God of Order, that he would be graciouſly pleaſed to give Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning Principles to right gathered Churches, and he would pleaſe ſo far to own and honour them, as to beſtow upon them the precious gifts of Diſcerning, Diſcretion, and Moderation towards all Perſons, upon all occaſions, and in all conditions; and more particular for the Spirit of Judgement and the ſpirit of Government: to order, eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:173115:27"/>and govern the Lords own People and Congregation, and to be found in the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſcharge of their great duty of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Juſtice, Mercy and Humility, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn the Churches with Juſt and Righteous Proceedings. That the Lords Name may be honoured, the Church rightly governed, the Truth renowned; that the fame of true Order may be more Proclaimed and further ſpread, that Strangers to it may be invited, Well-wiſhers may be engaged, Enemies may be prevented, and the Lords Faithfull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants may ever be encouraged and reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. By <hi>Excluſion,</hi> according to the Rule of Purging, putting out, cutting off, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication. Not always bearing &amp; for bearing ſuch as are common and impenitent Treſpaſſers,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12.</note> after prayers made, and other Chriſtian means Religiouſly and indifferently uſed and improved, and a conſiderable time and ſpace hath been waited and delayed, and yet all Counſells and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs are refuſed and rejected; Then to proceed gradually according to the Rule in that caſe provided, and to ſee that Diſcipline be rightly performed, and Juſtice duly exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, without knowing of Faces or regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:173115:27"/>Cauſes. For ſin is infectious, and a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe very dangerous and contagious. If hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Wiſedome teacheth us to ſeparate our ſelves from infected bodies, places, and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the ſafety of the outward man; much more doth ſpiritual diſcretion admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh us, and beſpeak us to ſeparate our ſelves from ſpirituall corruptions, and to exclude from us corrupted profeſſors, defiled, pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, impenitent Perſons, which ſo nearly relate to Soul matters, and ſo muchreſpects Immortal things <hi>For a little Leaven,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joſ.</hi> 7.11.</note> leaveneth the whole lump, The whole Camp of Iſrael stand charged for one Achan, and the Church of Corinth for one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous perſon.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2.</note> Though Juſtice be ſhoulder-work and a hard duty, yet 'tis better cut off a member then deſtroy the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Let all ſuch proceeding be attended with the face of Authority, the garments of Humility, and with arms of Mercy, with Patience and Compaſſion; deſigning to ſave the ſinner, by endeavouring to deſtroy his tranſgreſſion. So let the Church purge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their own and other mens ſins, by calling offendors into queſtion, and putting Chriſt's laws into execution. Thus I have tendred my judgement in order to obtain Right Government.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:173115:28"/>
               <head>Concerning Chriſtians as they stand related to civil Magiſtrates,</head>
               <p>NOw no man can be a good Governour, unleſſe he firſt knows the place and ſervice of an Inferiour; 'Tis therefore need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for us to know our ſtanding and relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and what's required of us in reſpect of ſubjection, as we are men and members of a Nation, and to be truly informed how we become concerned in duty, as we are placed in a politick body. We are taught by the holy Scriptures to know <hi>that there is no power but of God,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.12.3, 4, 5.</note> and whoſoever reſiſts the power, reſiſts the Ordinance of God.</hi> From thence we are inſtructed what the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Office is, even to puniſh evill doers, and to be a praiſe to them that do well: So alſo by the authority of the ſame Scriptures and holy writings, we are commanded and injoyned to be ſubject to civill powers in civill things, and that under the penalty of condign puniſhments: not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake; and we ought to obey not for fear of vengeance, but becauſe of a good conſcience. 'Tis alſo matter of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:173115:28"/>conſcience to obey good and profitable laws wherein our ſubmiſſion may tend to the civill peace of our Country and Nation,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.21.</note> 
                  <hi>and to give to Caeſar that which is Caeſars, and to God that which is Gods.</hi> 'Tis therefore our burthen to hear our ſelves miſreported, as if we were no well wiſhers to National Government, when as we look upon good Governours and good Government to be as great an external Priviledge and Bleſſing as any other in the World; and whereas the Lord knows we look upon our ſelves dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the holy Scriptures, and obliged by Goſpel Rules <hi>to be in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the higher Powers,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</note> to obey Magiſtrates, and to ſubmit our ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake</hi> (in the ſence aforeſaid) <hi>and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile them, or ſpeak evill of them, or to imagine evill in our hearts againſt them;</hi> For there is a tongue &amp; heart-murderer, as well as an eye and heart-Adulterer; but to ſtudy to know our Places &amp; Duties, as we are Inferiours,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.11.</note> and therein to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our conſciences, as we are Chriſtians, even to yield ſubmiſſion to them, and to pray for them, that we may lead a peaceable and godly life under them;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:173115:29"/>believing there ought to be Civil Magiſtrates in all Nations, and always rendring unto our Governours their due in tribute, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes reſerving and rendring unto God his due in worſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Concerning ſome Rules that reſpect and relate to Chriſtian Families.</head>
               <p>THe Rules which I have already tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and freely offered to Chriſt's Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, may be uſefull in every Family, and to every Chriſtian; which method is by <hi>Election, Direction, Correction, Protection, Supplication, Excluſion</hi> and <hi>Execution;</hi> And becauſe I will take in that which may be a good Second, and a ſpecial Aſſiſtant to this prime part of Religion, even Eccleſiaſticall Government, I will humbly tender the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Rules to believing Families, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially to the Heads and Overſeers, to look upon their ſeveral Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16.</note> that reſpect their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral duties and reſpective places. For when the Lord had created Man and Woman, he was pleaſed to appoint Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwixt them. I would therefore urge
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173115:29"/>the Argument of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Set thy Houſe in order becauſe of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.1.</note> that ye may be prepared when ye are called to dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. By <hi>Election,</hi> In making choiſe and placing your affections upon Vertuous and Religious Yoak-fellows in the Conjugall bond of Wives and Husbands; That may be ſuitable and meet helps, not only in reſpect of the concerns of the World, but more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in the matters of God; for ſuch are the beſt helps that are helps in the beſt things.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 36.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.39.</note> Let them therefore that are or may be in that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, firſt look for Piety, Gravity, and Fidelity; for ſuch bring good portions and great bleſſings with them into a Family. I could be ſevere againſt ſome Profeſſors, who offend in this caſe, and give ſuch great offences to others, who for Worldly Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, run into ſuch unequal and unmeet Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages; and others, that rather covet to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual or above in reſpect of Temporal porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than to be united in one in matters of Faith and Religion. Let Maſters make choiſe of ſuch Servants as truly fear the Lord;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſ.</hi> 101.6.</note> for how ſhould a man expect Gods Service ſhould be promoted, and good order obſerved, when a
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:173115:30"/>man ſhall take ſuch perſons into his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as are ſtrangers to the Rule of Truth and Verity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By <hi>Direction,</hi> By inſtructing and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them in the knowledge of the way and fear of the Lord, teaching his Laws and Oracles unto them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7.</note> begetting in them an affection and Reverence to his Will and Word, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting them with the bleſſings promiſed upon the believing and obeying Gods Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirements, and the dangers threatned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt neglectors, and the dreadfull Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that fall upon deſpiſers of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and orders. Let the Heads and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of this little Church or Kingdome (as I may call it) exerciſe the Office in an humble ſence of Prophet, Prieſt, and King; to teach them, to offer Sacrifice for them, and to govern them. Let believing Parents give their children Goſpel-breeding, and ſpiritual Education, that they may know how to behave themſelves in the Houſhold of God as becomes the Family of ſo Princely a Poſterity, and to learn the carriage of holy manners, and preciſely to prove all things like the <hi>Baereans,</hi> who by ſo doing, may be reputed truly Noble and well bred Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. I would reſpectively impoſe upon ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:173115:30"/>to take the place of Tutors, and their houſes to be as Nurceries of Learning, there to be inſtructed and prepared even to fit them to Degrees of Piety and Religion:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.6.</note> and for this take the Counſell of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who ſaith, <hi>Train up a Child in the way he ſhould go, and he will not depart from it when he is old:</hi> Mark, he ſaith <hi>he will not depart.</hi> Mind what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Bring up your Children in the Lords nurture and admonition, and ſo to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by good Counſel and good example to incline their hearts and conform their minds to ſound Doctrine, Goſpel-order, and a holy converſation, and ſo come to be made capable of ſpiritual Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and Church-Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. By <hi>Correction,</hi> By diſcountenancing, Correcting, Preventing and Reſtraining of ſin, to prevent and reform them from vanity and vice by the reproof of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere countenance and angry face,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.13. <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.14.</note> and to ſtop their growing into folly, and the bringing forth evill action, by rectifying all diſorders in their converſation, and this to be done timely and in due ſeaſon, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the beſt Rules of diſcretion, have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their diſpoſition; ſome to gain by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:173115:31"/>fear, and ſome by favour. Let the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances obſerved in <hi>Correction</hi> give evidence for a mans ſelf, his end is good in Correcting. I have heard at the common place of Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſome complaining of Fathers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of Maſters, becauſe they did not reſtrain them from vain Courſes; ſaying, if they had, it might have been a prevention of their ever coming to that ſhamefull Execution: And indeed God hath ſet Fathers and Maſters, as Rulers, and to have dominion within the borders of their Family, Juriſdiction, and doubtleſſe of their places they muſt give an account; Therefore they have great reaſon to diſcharge their truſt to their Inferiours, and to make uſe of their power and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, which are many, they having ſo much opportunity to diſcern into their actions, and to diſcover their lives, and to know their deſigns; and having ſo near a relation to them, and ſo great a command over them might be much inſtrumental (by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) to do much for God, and for their ſouls benefit and eternal good.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By <hi>Protection,</hi> By Countenancing and Cheriſhing the budding of grace, &amp; nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every appearance of God in the ſoul,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.</note> giving timely incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement and a ſeaſonable aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:173115:31"/>to the matters of Faith and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to be a guarding preſence to the ſmall beginning; not to quench the ſmoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Flax and bruiſed Reed, to mind them of ſpiritual Traffick, and to bring them up in the knowledge of ſpiritual Husbandry; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecting in them the heads of Grace and plants of Piety; uſing much diligence, waiting with tenderneſſe their growth and increaſe;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7.</note> For as the School-men ſay, <hi>The greatest Matters have the ſmalleſt Beginnings.</hi> The Seeds and Roots of Grace and Piety are like the tender Herbs and Plants that have need to be tenderly preſerved, to be often water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and weeded, and well fenced and ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. For a man is a Prince in his own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, to protect Order and Piety, and to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Sin and Iniquity; and having caſt out the things that offend, and well prepared the ground, the next thing is to put things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome Method, Form and Order. And here the Chriſtian profeſſor may learn a Leſſon of the Gardener, who in his Plantation and Garden, having gotten the choiſeſt Hearbs and Plants, he deviſes his form, and ſets them according to rule and order, both for profit, and alſo to delight the owner: So Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, when they have prepared Matter, they
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:173115:32"/>are to place them in the Lords Vineyard, and that in a Goſpel manner, that they may be fruitfull for their Lord and Maſter; and alſo to invite and delight the beholder to take them with Orders beauty: for it was the Order of <hi>Solomons</hi> Family that aſtoniſht the Queen of <hi>Sheba.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. By <hi>Supplication,</hi> For Family and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; always remembering the Lord is the Donor and Beſtower of all Gifts and Graces, and that we are but poor begging Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at the Throne of Grace, and Door of Mercy for our ſelves and Families, praying humbly and heartily that the Lord would pleaſe to Sanctifie all means, and Crown all endeavours with his own be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.5.</note> without which all other labours are nothing; for without him we can do nothing: fervently petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord that our Families might be his Family, that he would direct and bleſs us in our <hi>Election, Direction, Correction, Protection</hi> &amp; <hi>Excluſion;</hi> And that our Children might be his Children, and our Servants his Servants; that the Lord would pleaſe to ſeaſon their hearts with his Grace, enlighten their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by his Spirit, to ingage their affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions by his Love, and ſo to prepare them and conform them to his Will and Word;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:173115:32"/>That with <hi>Joſhua, We and our Houſes may ſerve the Lord;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſ.</hi> 24.15.</note> That as they grow in years and ſtrength, ſo they may increaſe in Knowledge and Goodneſſe, that they might be Plants in his Houſe, and placed in his Family, and ſo be fruitfull Inſtruments of his Glory, and humbly to offer Sacrifice for them, and to intercede the Lord, that they might orderly obey his Doctrine, and cheerfully ſubmit to his Diſcipline, and to intreat his favour to guide them by his Counſell here, and receive them into his Kingdome hereafter.</p>
               <p n="6">6. By <hi>Excluſion;</hi> Yet here I do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend in the leaſt to meddle with Wife and Children, no more than to purge ſin out of them;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.16.</note> but in this caſe I mind only Servants, Buſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodies and Tale-bearers, which are oft-times Inſtruments of Diſorder and Diſturbance in many Families; And as the Wiſe man ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Where there is no wood the Fire goeth out;</hi> So where there is no Tale-bearer, Strife ceaſeth. And for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants that are vain &amp; diſorderly, may in time infect and corrupt the reſt in a Family. Now 'tis better to remove and exclude ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, than that they ſhould defile and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:173115:33"/>many others, that ye may keep Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline within your Familie Dominion: there is for this a good example of <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.6, 7.</note> who ſaith, <hi>Men of Faithfulneſſe and Integrity ſhall dwell with me, and ſerve me.</hi> But he would not keep a Lyar about him, nor he that worketh deceit ſhould neither dwell in his Houſe, nor tarry in his ſight. Thus every man within his own Juriſdiction may exerciſe Family Diſcipline, both to teach, intercede and govern, and by diligence and prudence may be an Inſtrument to bring his Houſe in order in Gods Service.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Let all theſe things be put into due execution, without which the knowledge of them comes to nothing. Every man to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe himſelf in his place faithfully, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct and govern his Family conſonant to to the Rules of Piety, and Principles of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and to act by the Law of Equity to all under them, as men in ſome ſence obliged to give an account of them.</p>
               <p>Theſe things conſidered, and calling to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance my place of truſt in Gods Houſe, and our ſpecial Obligations each to other as we are Chiſtians, I can do no leſſe than ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe, warn, exhort and intreat you, according to the relation, I ſtand with you, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:173115:33"/>I have in you, to put your duties into practices, and remove out of your Families all offences and diſorders;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.8. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21.</note> for ye know we ought not to bear with ſin, to regard Cauſes, or reſpect Perſons, although they be our near relations: but to do Juſtice with Equity, and that without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay or partiality; for we may not harbour evils, nor ſuffer diſorder in our Families, and that we have no juſt complaining in our ſtreets. 'Tis true we cannot expect mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Families ſhould be free from all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; where then would be the uſe of bearings and forbearings? Beware of Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braiding and Retorting Languages which oft-times creates diſcontents, and raiſes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances in Families. There ought rather to be found among Chriſtians a condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to each others diſpoſitions, concerning their deformities, bearing one anothers weakneſſes, and if it may be to determine Family-failings, within the compaſſe of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily Jurisdictions, and to endeavour to bear one anothers burdens, and ſo fulfill the Law of Chriſt. To ſympathize with each other in temptations and afflictions; that ye may not make your lives a burden to your ſelves, and a trouble and grief to others: for conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:173115:34"/>that miſcarriages among Chriſtians are attended with high aggravations. Firſt, a diſhonour to God, a diſcredit to the truth, a diſparagement to Profeſſors, a grief to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, a ſorrow to well-wiſhers, a bondage to themſelves, and a rejoycing to their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. My adviſe is therefore for the time paſt, wherein any of you have offended each other, to repent it, and wherein others have treſpaſſed againſt you, upon their ſubmiſſion pardon it; &amp; let all former things be laid dead, and buried in the grave of Oblivion, no more to be remembred, or have any more Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, to diſquiet your peace here, or to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence againſt you hereafter. And for the time to come, my Counſel &amp; Exhortation is, to ſet the fear of the Lord before you, &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve one anothers tempers; conſider each others frailties, and when ye have any thing to ſay, remember to take ſuitable ſeaſons; endeavouring to remove Jelouſies, avoid all occaſions that may tend to provocations, and if poſſible let all be ſwallowed up in dear af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, which beſt becomes ſuch near Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and moſt adorns profeſſing Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:173115:34"/>
               <head>But yet a few words more particularly, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects every Houſe and Family to divide their Duties to each other, and that ſeverally.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HUsbands ought to love their Wives, as Chriſt loved the Church, and as they love themſelves, and to rule over them with much Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25.28.</note> and to govern with diſcretion, and commend their ſubmiſſion by the power of a free and conſtant affection: to imitate the Lords Pattern, who loved his Spouſe better than himſelf; covering deformities, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infirmities, taking part with them in their Diſtreſſes, attending them with neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Accommodations and ſuitable conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences at all times and in all conditions; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring both are but one fleſh; and that a mans wife is half himſelf; conſidering ſhe is a Building of the greater Admiration; and being brought to man, holds forth the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Honour and Perfection of Gods Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Likewiſe Husbands are to dwell with their Wives according to Knowledge, having reſpect to their weakneſſes, and to honour
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:173115:35"/>them as the weaker Veſſels; For the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is the glory of the Man, and yet under his Authority, to teach her ſubjection, and to ſhew him he is her protection.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Wives ought to ſubmit themſelves to their own Husbands as unto the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25.</note> Remembring 'tis Gods own Inſtitution, That man ſhould Rule and have the Dominion, and Woman ſhould o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey and be in Subjection: and God hath Ordained and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored men to be Heads and Superiours;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16.</note> and as the Church is ſubject to Chriſt, ſo ought Wives to be to their own Husbands; and that Gods own Order and Ordinance might be owned and adorned. Let them imitate <hi>Sarah,</hi> who obeyed <hi>Abraham,</hi> and called him Lord. Thus in old time the holy Women put on the Ornament of a meek and quiet ſpirit, which well becomes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian, and is much ſet by in the ſight of God and man. Let Wives then give that Reverence and freely yield that due ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to their Husbands which God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them; alwayes endeavouring to approve themſelves ſuitable aſſiſtants, and meet helps, according as they were firſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and appointed to be a comfortable Nurſe and Yoak-fellow, to rejoyce them,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:173115:35"/>and to be a conſtant ſuccour and comfort to them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Parents ought to educate and bring up their Children in the nurture and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord, and by good Counſel and ſound inſtruction to diſcharge their duties to them in matters of Faith and Religion;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 9.4.</note> and as God hath bleſſed you with Children, ſo perſwade your Children to be Inſtruments of Glory to him, and to make known to them their natural affection, according to the neerneſſe of their Relation; avoyding temptations and occaſions of their provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Let every man exerciſe his fatherly care with Providence and Moderation, to make a comfortable proviſion for them; endeavouring to match and prefer them to ſuch as truly fear the Lord, and act and walk conſonant to the Rule and Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his Word.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Children ought to obey their Parents in the Lord, and to honour Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.1.</note> this is Gods Precept, for ſo ſaith the Word, acknowledging them duty and obedience, and rendring them their due in Reverence, confeſſing their propriety in them and their authority over them; to command them
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:173115:36"/>and diſpoſe of them freely, to obſerve their inſtructions, &amp; patiently ſubmit to their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, knowing that children which are Inferiours, being diſobedient to Parents, their Superiours in ſo neer a Relation, is an offence with a high aggravation: Firſt, 'tis a ſin againſt God the Author of Family-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. 'Tis a ſin againſt man, which God hath appointed as his Vicegerent. 'Tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own father, and ſo 'tis unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and contrary to the light of Nature. But let children humbly obey their Parents, and ſee that they do their duties; ſo may they expect in due time to inherit Gods promiſed bleſſings.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Maſters which alſo ſtand in the place of Superiours, and may do much for God in their places, and by that power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand they have under God and over their Servants, by reſtraining them from vice and vanity, and by giving liberty and incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in acts of Vertue and Piety. Maſters are to give unto their Servants that which is equall and juſt, knowing they have a Maſter in Heaven,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 4.1.9.</note> who reſpects not Perſons but juſt and equall dealings. They alſo are to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear Threatnings and oppreſſings, becauſe whatſoever is meaſured to another by any
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:173115:36"/>man, the ſame meaſure ſhall be meaſured to him back again.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Servants ought to obey and ſubmit to their Maſters in all things as unto the Lord; not only to the gentle and good, but to ſuch alſo of them as are froward; not with eye ſervice as men-pleaſers, but with ſingleneſs of heart as the Servants of Chriſt, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging their power by obeying their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, ſtriving topleaſe them wel in all things not anſwering again,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.9, 10.</note> nor pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyning; walking in all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, and ſhewing all Fidelity, that in all ſervices, and by all means they may adorn the Doctrine of Chriſt in all things.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And Laſtly, Let every one do their duties in their ſeveral Obligations, whether Superiours or Inferiours. I may adde to the reſt, Land-lords and Tenants, who ought to deal faithfully each to other as unto the Lord. Land-lords are in ſuch places, and have great advantages to do good ſervices, if they do improve themſelves for the Lord, and give good Councel to their Tenants, according to his Holy Word. Let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member although they are Landlords to men, yet they are but Tenants and Stewards to the God of Heaven; Who hath the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all things, who can increaſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:173115:37"/>at pleaſure, and gives and takesaway as he pleaſeth: &amp; as they expect Obedience, Dues and Juſt accounts of their Tenants, So the Lord, the great Land-lord, expects his Obedience, Dues, and juſt accounts, as we ſtand his Tenants and Servants. Let Tenants alſo deal faithfully and do equally in Juſtice,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.2.12.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the good Rule of doing as a man would be done by; acting according to the laws of Righteouſneſſe towards God, and the Principles of Uprightneſs towards men: For whoſoever ſhall make a breach upon the Rules of equity and equal dealing, the Lord will requite them in Juſtice anſwerable to the Law of Retalliation. But let Superiours know the limits of their Commands, which is over Bodies and not Conſciences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Some Rules concerning private and perſonal Government.</head>
               <p>EVery particular perſon is charged with a ſouls protection; and it being a weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty imployment to be charged with a Souls Concernment,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.8.</note> it being of a greater value than
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:173115:37"/>can be reckoned the gain and loſſe of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more than the gain and loſſe of the whole World. Let the former Rules be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon once again in order to perſonal Regulation. For there we ought to begin the Foundation, for the better accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the great work of Church-Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for although this come laſt, 'tis none of the leaſt works to be done, and that which pertains to every Chriſtian man to ſet and keep things in order at home in this little World and more private Juriſdiction. For 'tis the greateſt piece of Knowledge for a man to know the depth of himſelf, and the higheſt Conqueſt for a man to overcome himſelf; and the moſt excellent part of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, when a man can rightly order his own heart, govern his own life, and rule well his own ſpirit.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.32.</note> 'Tis not only reported but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced, that Heart-work is the moſt difficult work; to which we had need uſe all the means that may be allowed, and to make uſe of all the helps that can be obtained.</p>
               <p n="1">1. By <hi>Election;</hi> As the Univerſal Lord hath ſet too great Lights to rule in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall World, and hath appointed Guides
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:173115:38"/>and Overſeers to enlighten and govern the Church of God; ſo hath he been graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſed to make Heavenly proviſion, to order and rule the Inner man; and as the Lord in his matchleſs love hath freely ſent his Son to ranſome us from everlaſting ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, ſo he hath freely given his Spirit to conductous towards eternal felicity.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 5.32.</note> Let every one then chooſe &amp; imbrace that means God hath Ordained for the obtaining and receiving Gods holy Spirit, which with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence I may truly call, The prime Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer over the Soul; he is the great Teacher, Leader and Conducter of the Saints, and whoſe Office may be fitly compared to the Office of an Overſeer or Ruler. He is the Chriſtians guide to enlighten and direct them, to ſanctifie and comfort them, to ſtrengthen and confirm them, to improve and quicken them to duties; and likewiſe he helps our infirmities, interprets our groans, and preſents our ſupplications, and makes requeſts for Saints according to the will of God. The bodies of Saints are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, and the Tabernacle of God, where he dwels and governs accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his word; he helps us to mortifie our ſins, and is grieved at our Tranſgreſſions.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:173115:38"/>Thus is the Kingdome of Heaven within you agreeable as the Scripture hath expreſt; which conſiſts of Righteouſneſſe, Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt. He alſo convinceth the World of Sin, ſtrives and waits upon man to correct and conform them, the Goſpel Order and holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo.</hi> 16.13.</note> and ſo guides the ſaints in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truth, and ſhews them things to come. Secondly, Conſcience may be called an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeer in a more ſubordinate and limited ſence, which the Lord hath ſet in man, which is the Epitome and Breviate of the World, which will act for God, and aſſiſt for the Souls ſpiritual good; ſerving to rule and order the whole man, even to regulate and Record every word and action. The Office of Conſcience is to oppoſe ſin, reprove ſin, condemn for ſin; and if the ſinner be impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, it terrifies and torments the ſinner, and like a faithfull friend, firſt tell him of his fault ſecretly; if he amends, 'tis forgiven by God freely; but if not, Conſcience either diſcovers it to be judged here,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15.</note> or elſe bears witneſſe againſt them at the Bar of Judgement hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But Conſcience will do Juſtice in it's Office; for it will excuſe if guiltleſſe, and bear teſtimony to a mans ſimplicity and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:173115:39"/>ſincerity, and upon every pious action it miniſters joy to the Inner-man. I may adde the light of Nature, which I may call a help in this perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Government,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14.</note> which in morall things will give information, and tell a man of ſin. Theſe helps, with a mans own endeavour, may (by Gods bleſſings) come to ſet his houſe in order.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By <hi>Direction;</hi> To give a mans ſelf up to be directed and taught by the dictates of Gods holy Spirit, ſubmitting to the Laws and Oracles of the Spirits adminiſtrations;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.2.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his Rules and Orders his firſt and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Councellors, giving heed to the,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119.24.</note> motions and preſſings of the ſpirit, and to the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the light within. For although ſome diſſenting friends may Idolize it, yet I warn the brethren that they no way deſpiſe it, but obſerve Conſcience in it's Informations and Incouragements, in it's Reproof, Recalls, and Chidings; for Officer-like it praiſes for well doing, and reproves and puniſhes for evill acting. Let Gods goodneſſe be admired in aſſigning ſuch helps for us, in ſetting ſuch lights in us, and Overſeers over us, to watch for us, to ſtrive with us, to aſſiſt and help us,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:173115:39"/>to govern our hearts and houſes when as we cannot help our ſelves: Let theſe Lights and Guides be conſulted with, and ſubmitted to, well obſerving their Counſell and Direction in order to a better Regulation, and that within the Precincts of this Perſonal Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
               <p>Beware of grieving and quenching the Spirit, and of reſiſting and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Conſcience,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.30.</note> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhing the light the Lord hath placed in us; but rather humbly to accept and reverently to entertain the Lords Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19.</note> as the Lord welcomes poor converted ſinners, even to affect them, to imbrace them, to delight in them, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them, highly to prize them, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in them, and to be thankful for them. Theſe things being well obſerved, God might be more glorified, the heart better commanded, and the Soul more rejoyced. For a man to till his own ground is the beſt Husbandry, and a man is moſt diſcreet when he is wiſe for Eternity. A mans chiefeſt work is to ſtudy his own condition, to take himſelf to cure, and become his own Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. To conclude this point, let every Chriſtian take care for his ſouls nutriment,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:173115:40"/>it's holy Ornament, i'ts ſpiritual Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and eternal Preferment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By <hi>Correction,</hi> By afflicting, judging, and correcting a mans ſelf for good omitted, and for evill committed againſt a gracious and holy God, who waits to be gracious to do our Souls good,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.9.</note> and to reſiſt the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the fleſh; and as the Apoſtle ſpeaks to beat down and keep under the body,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27.</note> &amp; bring it into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and to exerciſe the ſpiritual ſword, to revenge all diſobedience, and pull down the ſtrong holds of ſin; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the guides in this prime and more private Kingdome; and in all ſouls dangers to take care to ingage their aſſiſtance, who will be faithfull for a mans ſecurity, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the War againſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual enemy;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.</note> and becauſe the heart is deceitfull and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous, &amp; will be ready to comply with the Souls enemies, and ſo beget an inward and home-bred war, which will grieve the Spirit, diſquiet the Conſcience, darken the Light, and endanger the Soul. Beware therefore Chriſtians, and endeavour to prevent theſe dangers: let every one ſtand upon their watches. The Chriſtians task is a double
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:173115:40"/>watch, the one to keep the heart from extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies, and the other to keep the enemy from approaches;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.23.</note> as the Wiſe man ſpeaks, <hi>above all, keeping watch over the heart with all diligence;</hi> for if he take the heart, the Tower of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, then will all be in danger to be yielded to the power of the adverſary, and then he will turn all members as Inſtruments to ſerve Iniquity, the foot to walk to do Impiety, the ears to hear Folly, the eyes to behold Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the tongue to ſpeak corruptly. Thus ſin when it's conceived in the womb of the heart, and is nouriſhed and nurſed there, in time comes to look out at the windows of the eyes, and breaks out at the door of the mouth, and ſo brings all out of order, and brings the ſoul into imminent danger; for he that hath not rule over his own ſpirit is like a City with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out walls,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 25.28.</note> 
                  <hi>And be that bridles not his tongue, that mans Religion is vain;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides he lies open to be taken and carried captive by the ſpiritual enemy, and ſo in danger of being inſlaved in everlaſting mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By <hi>Protection;</hi> Keep thy ſoul with all diligence, for 'tis the beſt policy for a man to make proviſion for his ſouls ſecurity, make
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:173115:41"/>the Name of God thy Caſtle of retreat,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.9.</note> and his promiſes thy chief Tower and refuge of defence, take to thy ſelf all the armour of God, eſpecially the ſhield of Faith,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 18.10.</note> and the Goſpel-ſword. I would have the Reader do in this caſe as a Prince had done for his own ſafety and protection, who kept his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers alwayes armed; being demanded why he did ſo, he replyed, How did he know which way, at what time, and with what power the enemy would come upon him? This may be fitly applyed by every Chriſtian who hath a precious ſoul to preſerve, and a politick &amp; potent enemy to encounter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, who ſometimes preſents guilded baits, and beautifull temptations to betray and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare innocent ſouls, and other times by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall ſtormes and dreadfull apparitions to fear and drive us from our faith and holy reſolutions. Chriſtians of all others had need to be furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and armed with ſpiritual weapons,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.11.13.</note> becauſe they are the moſt provided and ſtored with Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Graces and Soul-Treaſures, and that's the cauſe the evill one is ſo frequent and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent in their borders; for their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection;
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:173115:41"/>Let Chriſtians act like Gariſon-men, examine all that go and come, and like the Temple-men, to let in the Holy, &amp; keep out the unclean; and alſo like the Sea-men, if the Veſſell leak, they ſpeedily caſt it out again. Be wiſe, and ſet a watch before the door of the heart, and three outward guards at the ſeveral Ports, before the Mouth, the Eyes, and the Ears, that nothing be conveyed in or our at theſe paſſages, that may prove the Souls deſtructive enemies. For the more certainty and better ſecurity, obſerve theſe ſhort Rules;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Get all things within into Order, Peace, and Unity; for Concord and Unitly like wall to a City.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Get thy ſelf ſtored and armed with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Artillery.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Wait and watch the motions and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of thy ſubtill adverſary.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Manage with courage all Combats and Encounters to obtain the Conqueſt and Victory.</p>
               <p n="5">5. By <hi>Supplication;</hi> By Verbal, Mentall, and Cordiall Prayers, to ask with the mouth, to ſeek with the heart, and knock by the hand of Faith;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.18.</note> Let Gods free grace, the prime and effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cauſe of all ſafety and ſucceſſe; be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:173115:42"/>admired, and thankfully acknowledged, and by a conſtant and fervent interceding the Throne of Grace for Gods bleſſing to ſeaſon and ſanctifie all means and endeavours.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.7.</note> The effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual and fervent prayer of a Righteous man availeth much; being mixed with Faith, obtaineth Vertue and Power from God, to aſſiſt and us to order and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern our ſelves according to his Word,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.16.</note> and that he would be graciouſly pleaſed to ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and quicken us to our duties, to teach us to number our days, to improve us by his Spirit, ſupply us with his grace, relieve us by his power, protect us by his providence, to furniſh us with Might in the Inner-man, to know our ſelves, to rule our own houſes, to command our own ſpirits, that we may be patterns of Order and Government to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther believers, and that he would be intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to learn us ſpiritual Art and holy Skill, to defend and ſecure our ſelves our ſouls and Soul-Treaſures againſt all the wiles and poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of our grand enemies, that having the Rule over our own ſpirit, we may be as him that hath taken a City, and obtained the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt over the great Adverſary, and ſo by Gods grace we may be ſafely conducted
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:173115:42"/>through all Combats and Temptations, and at laſt received into Everlaſting Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p n="6">6. By <hi>Excluſion;</hi> To exclude all falſe Counſels, fooliſh conceits and vain imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations from the heart,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.31, 22.</note> and to baniſh all lurking luſts and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd pretences from the Court of the Inner-man. But in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Executing and Effecting this good Work, let every ſoul apart call and keep a private and particular Court within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of his own perſonal dominion, and let this judgement be holden as Gods ſpirit hath given Charge and Commiſſion, and ſo to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the power of a juſt and righteous go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and to bring every word and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into judgement: and becauſe the heart is deceitfull and will oft-times diſguiſe it ſelf, and evade the truth, and is full of windings and turnings,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.21.</note> and falſe pleadings. Let every one take an exact and legall way of tryall, and a ſtrict and formal way of Judgement, and ſo proceed to Examination, Probation,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 28.26.</note> Condemnation and Execution; and let all be done according to Law and Truth. For a man may do Injuſtice upon himſelf: Let Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:173115:43"/>ſit as Judge, for Conſcience will ſide with the Lord, and judge for God and for the ſouls good. Let the pure Law of God conteined in his Word be the Rule to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by; let the knowing and underſtanding part be the witneſſes to give in the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to every action, and againſt every Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of evill doing; let all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Soul and body be as Jurors, and call in every miſcariage to make up the clearneſſe of the Evidence, which is the ground and guide of Juſtice. Let the Law and the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence be equally compared, and neither bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome nor ſecret ſins be reſpected; that the Old man with his deeds may be caſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and the body of ſin executed and deſtroyed, and buried in the grave of Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vion, never to have any more Reſurrection; Either to diſquiet our peace here, or to evidence againſt us hereafter; knowing the terrour of the Lord moves me to be earneſt to perſwade.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31.</note> For if we would judge our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged of the Lord, neither condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the World. Let us therefore beware and ſin no more, for behold the great Judge ſtands before the door.</p>
               <p n="7">7. By <hi>Execution;</hi> To put perſonal Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline into due Execution, without which all
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:173115:43"/>is nothing; for practice is the life of the Law, for if the practick part be neglected, the bleſſing will not be obtained, and that becauſe the condition is unperformed. Let all perſons learn to command and rule them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and eſpecially Superiours, who ſhould command and rule others. For if a man knows not how to command himſelf, how ſhould he command Inferiours; and as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>If a man knows not how to rule his own houſe, how ſhould he take care of the Church of God?</hi> According to the old ſaying, If every man would rightly order and govern one, 'tis the ready way to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the whole Congregation. I hope the words I have written touching perſonal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation will not be thought ſo Impertinent, but that they being timely applyed &amp; ſutably improved, may tend to the furthering and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing a Righteous Government. And as I have been ſpeaking of ſome particulars touching the governing a mans life, ſo I would adde a few words by way of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance what is to be ſet in order at or before a mans death. I will ground my ſpeech up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> to King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 38.1.</note> who was commanded to ſet his Houſe in order becauſe he ſhould not live
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:173115:44"/>but dye: we being all under the ſentence of Mortality, become concerned to ſet our houſes in order ſpeedily. Doubtleſſe as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> was a King, he was under a great care to ſet and leave things in order within his dominion, and as he was head of a Family to ſet things in order within his Family-Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, and as he was a ſervant and child of God to ſet his accounts in order according to his Will and Word; ſo is every Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an concerned within the compaſſe of his place and power, as he may have the charge of a Congregation or the charge of a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and the charge of his own ſoul, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our truſt and do our duty, and ſo ſet our houſe in order before we dye. <hi>Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah's</hi> pattern is a good precedent for every mans direction to prepare our reckoning, to form and preſent our accounts. Mark well what he ſaith, in Verſe the third,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.3.</note> in giving up his Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts to the Lord, ſaying, 1. <hi>I have walked before thee in truth;</hi> 2. <hi>And have done that with a perfect heart;</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>And that which is good in thy ſight.</hi> This is but a brief and ſhort breviate, but it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains an excellent and full account. 1. I have not talked, but I have walked not before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers but before thee, not in Error but in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:173115:44"/>Truth. 2. Not in ſhew but in heart; not with a double and impure heart, but with a upright and perfect heart. 3. He doth not ſay he would and will do, but I have done, not that which is vain, but that which is good; not in the ſight of men, but in the ſight of God. To be ſhort, let theſe words be laid to heart; For God is exact and will view every mans Account,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</note> for we muſt all appear at the Judgement Seat; See that ye have prepared a good account to preſent in the day of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts. 2. As every Chriſtian is to ſet things in order to account with God;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.12.</note> ſo he is to leave behind him ſome examples of Piety to the World, that his orderly life, zeal for godlineſſe, and his acts of charity, when he is no more, may perfume his memory, and be like <hi>Abels</hi> Sacrifice, to ſpeak after he dyes, and may be worthy of Imication to Church-family, and Neighbour-hood Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 3. As touching temporal ſubſtance, that the Lord hath made a man Maſter of, or rather Steward over. He is likewiſe to ſet in order to diſcharge his place and Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard ſhip faithfully; that he may have peace when he is called to dye. To diſpoſe and divide his wordly goods and earthly poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:173115:45"/>timely and equally, agreeable to the Righteous rules of Religion and the beſt principles of Equity and Reaſon, both to Yoke-fellow and Poſterity; or for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for whom he may be intruſted or obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; either to widdows or to fatherlerleſſe, and both towards God &amp; men to diſcharge a good conſcience. 4. To conſider and ponder well to ſettle all things ſo ſtraight and juſt between them that may prevent all future ſtrife &amp; diſcord among them; that none may juſtly ſay when he is gone, he is the man that did, or cauſed this or that wrong: this being Religiouſly obſerv'd, many injuries &amp; quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rells would be prevented, and ſo peace and love may be preſerved. 5. If any one ſhall be like to depart this preſent life, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of this Worlds goods, and hath no natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Heirs or near Relations: let him not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get but remember to communicate to the poor Chriſtians; let them make the Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons of the Churches their Overſeers, and the poor Saints their Executors. Let all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, but ſuch in a ſpeciall manner; Or elſe to bequeath his Wealth and Treaſures to ſome pious and publick ſervices; in ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they will honour their Profeſſion, and lay up for themſelves a good foundation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the time to come.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:173115:45"/>
               <p> Some may think I am out of the way in leaving the Churches and turning into Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and treating with particular perſons. Let them know I have been in the Churches ſervice, attending and inſtructing Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members apart in their own houſes, and to inſtruct them in their Family-duties and Church-Orders; Inciting them and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to prepare their Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants for members to people the Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>6. <hi>The true Order and right manner of the Execution of Church Government.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IUſtice and Judgement are the ſubſtantial parts of Church government. Juſtice is a great word, and the action is a ſhoulder work,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſai.</hi> 9.7.</note> and being in it's Execution, carries a great commendation. It advanceth Chriſts Honour, promotes Truths Credit, renowns Chriſts Churches; It breaks Sathans deſigns, promotes good Cauſes, prevents and diſturbs evill inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and rejoyces Chriſts innocent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. In my further proſecution of this matter I would obſerve this following or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. What Juſtice and Diſcipline is in it ſelf.</item>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:173115:46"/>
                  <item>2. What, or who are the offenders upon whom it is to be executed.</item>
                  <item>3. What is to be underſtood and obſerved in it's proſecution.</item>
                  <item>4. What priviledges are to be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Chriſts Congregation.</item>
                  <item>5. What diſorders are to be prevented, corrected and removed.</item>
                  <item>6. Some branches of Injuſtice and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to be avoided.</item>
                  <item>7, How the Execution it ſelf ſhould be rightly performed.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Firſt, What Juſtice is; it conſiſts of theſe general parts: an Offender, an Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, a Law, and a penalty. Juſtice in it's Execution is, when a faithfull power ſhall inflict puniſhment upon a convicted Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, conſonant to the true intent of the Law in that caſe provided, and the Execution per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without delay or partiality.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What are the Offenders and offences againſt whom Juſtice is to be executed. Firſt, There are private faults and offences that are committed between Brother and Brother: in which caſe the injured or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded brother is to tell his brother offending,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.</note> of his fault betwixt them alone; If he hear not, take one or two more, If he neglect to hear them tell it
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:173115:46"/>to the Church, if he neglect to hear them, then let the Church do their duty, and purge themſelves of iniquity; For as a man will haſten to purge poyſon out of his body cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, much more ought Chriſtians to purge ſin out of the body ſpiritual; But if thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hears thee and repents of the evill heartily, thou oughteſt to forgive him free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fully and perpetually. But if it ſhall happen that any two perſons ſhall oppoſe each other,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.18.</note> in and about a matter and fault committed, and have no other witneſſe but themſelves, and there can be neither pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual nor circumſtantial proof made to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide the controverſie; then doubtleſſe 'tis the Churches duty and liberty to make their humble appeal to the God of Heaven, by caſting lots,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.18. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.13. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.26.</note> and making ſerious ſupplications tohim, that he would be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to order and diſpoſe of the lot for their direction, to ſhew which of thoſe two was the guilty perſon: and when the Lord hath diſcovered him, let the Church do their duty that concerns them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:173115:47"/>
               <head>Concerning RESTITUTION.</head>
               <p>IF an Offender do confeſſe his fault, and promiſe an amendment, let him make Reſtitution for that wrong he hath done.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.12.</note> For as it is a great part of Juſtice, ſo 'tis a very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary part of Repentance; for it repayes a juſt recompence for injuries done, and 'tis a very great deſtruction to ſin. How can a man expect his ſin ſhould be pardoned,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jud.</hi> 1.7.</note> before the wrong he hath done be repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or that be reſtored which he hath unju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly took and wrongfully detained. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe if a man injure his brother in body, goods or good name, he ſtands bound in Juſtice to make him reaſonable Reſtitution, and this is congruous with Gods righteous Law of Retaliation; For oftimes Juſtice re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quits and inflicts puniſhment in the ſame Act in which a man hath ſinned.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.2.</note> This alſo concurs with the Law Chriſt hath given, which ſaith, In effect, what meaſure a man meaſures to another in ſin, the ſame ſhall be meaſured to him in puniſhment back again.</p>
               <div type="directions">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:173115:47"/>
                  <head>Concerning Hereticks.</head>
                  <p>An Heretick, after the firſt and ſecond ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition reject or caſt away; becauſe one corrupted perſon may corrupt the whole body,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10, 11.</note> being one that is perverted or willingly turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide from the Truth; an Actor of Sexts, or maintainer of a falſe belief, and hath ſubverted or overthrown himſelf; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting the true Religion, and ſo becomes an inſtrument of his own condemnation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="directions">
                  <head>Concerning dealing with publick Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders.</head>
                  <p>Such as ſin openly are to be rebuked pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, and the Church is to withdraw from every one that walks diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6.14.</note> that he may be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of his Iniquity, and that every particular ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition and publick with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing may put others in fear and be as a general warning. Now touching ſuch ſinners mentioned in the Fifth of the <hi>Corinthians;</hi> There is ſome ſmall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance between ſome faithfull Chriſtians:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:173115:48"/>Whether ſuch offenders there noted may be received into Communion if they be pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent; ſome judging, if they repent they may be received; others judging, although they do confeſſe their ſin, yet the Church ought to withdraw from them. I confeſſe they plead reaſon on both ſides. One al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging thus, That if that end be already accompliſht for which the Ordinance of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication was appointed, what need or reaſon is there the perſon ſhould be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded? Others reply, If the ſinner be not ſpeedily ſentenced, the Church will be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened, and that for ſuch publick and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſins, by which God is ſo highly diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored, and the Church ſo greatly reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The Church cannot be purged untill the guilty perſon be puniſhed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Christian Reader,</hi> As touching this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I will preſume to take the place of a Moderator; for I have heard the queſtion debated among able men, who in the main agree and deſign the ſelf ſame thing, there's only a form of words betwixt them, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree the ſinner ſhall be called into queſtion: The one admoniſhes him for his evill in the Name of the Lord; The other paſſeth a ſentence againſt him by the power of the ſame Lord; both rebuke the perſon for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:173115:48"/>the wickedneſſe done, both bear their teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony againſt the crime, in order to clear the Church of his Tranſgreſſion; both diſ-pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge the Tranſgreſſor of Communion, untill he appears a truly humbled perſon, and gives the Congregation full ſatisfaction: ſo that in truth upon the whole matter there is no material ſubſtance that's worthy to bear the name of a difference; ſo that for my own part, for peace ſake, I could conſent either wayes; provided the beſt care be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by all that are concerned, That Gods Honour be preſerved, all ſcandall be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the Truths Innocency delivered, and the Churches Reputation vindicated.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>3. <hi>What is to be underſtood and obſerved in the prroſecution of Diſcipline</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt, There is ſteps and Circumſtances to be obſerved in reproving; 1. Timely, 2. Affectionately. 3. A private fault pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately. 4. To deſign the reſtoring the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from iniquity. Concerning Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, let this order be obſerved. 1. Let it be done in Chriſts Name and Authority. 2. See that ſinner be convicted legally. 3. Let the Counſell and Bleſſing of God be
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:173115:49"/>ſought fervently. 4. To the end the fleſh may be deſtroyed, and the ſpirit ſaved in the day of the Lord. Repentance conſiſts of four parts, 1. Contrition of the heart. 2. Confeſsion of the mouth. 3. Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the life. 4. Reſtitution for the wrong done. An order in forgiveneſs, 1. It muſt be groundedly. 2. Freely, 3. Fully, 4. Perpetually. There is a method to be obſerved in Prayer, as our Lord hath taught us ſaying, when we pray, pray after this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. When Duties want their Order and Circumſtance, they are oft-times rejected, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of being accepted; for 'tis evident God requires equal ſubmisſion to order as he doth to the duty it ſelf. The Wiſe man <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, He would put his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs in order.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.9.</note> In all Gods former ſervices about the Ark, Alter and Sanctuary, the Lord preciſely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired all perſons to attend reſpectively their Offices and places, and that all things ſhould exactly be ſet in order and appointed to their ſeveral uſes; and for the breach in Order,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 19.13.</note> the Lord in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger cauſed ſome deeply to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſembling, and about Propheſying, and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lords Supper, he ſums up all with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:173115:49"/>this charge, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</note> The ſame Apoſtle beholds, rejoyceth, commends, and praiſes the order of the <hi>Coloſſians.</hi> Doubtleſs there ought to be ſome method in Preaching: 'Tis great pitty that divine and pure matter ſhould want its beauty and ornament of form and order. St. <hi>Paul</hi> commands <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>study to ſhew himſelf a workman, rightly dividing the Word of truth.</hi> There is a Rule to be obſerved in hearing; 1. Preparation to hear. 2. At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in hearing. 3. Meditation after hearing. 4. Supplication before and after a bleſsing. There are ſteps and degrees in believing; 1. The faith of credence. 2. The faith of adherence. 3. The faith of endurance. 4. Of ſtedfaſt reliance. A Rule to be obſerved in ſuffering; 1. To have a good cauſe. 2. A right call. 3. A good conſcience. 4. A pure end. To be ſhort, there ought to be an order in all obedience, in reſpect of matter, manner, end, and circumſtance; for the righteous God as truely-puniſhes for the breach of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as he doth for neglect of ſervices. As order is the ornament of profeſsion, ſo I may call it the maſter-piece of Religion, for both Gods precepts for it, and puniſhments upon
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:173115:50"/>the neglect of it, witneſs the ſame. There ought to be a ſtrict order in the commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords Supper, even to hold and keep it with ſuch obſervation,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</note> as may anſwer to the firſt inſtitution; and in preſuming to come to ſuch holy Myſteries, there ought to be great heart-preparations, and ſelf exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; 1. In unity of heart, judgement, and affection. 2. In purity of life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. 3. Reverently, as being at the Table and in the preſence of the God of Heaven.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 86.11.</note> 4 Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an eye to the end, which is the victory Chriſt hath obtained for every Chriſtian. 5. To act in charity, and freely, becauſe love was the firſt cauſe of our felicity. 6. Rejoycingly, as men having intereſt in the ſpirituall conqueſt over our ſouls adverſary, and as men purchaſed from everlaſting miſery. 7. Thankfully, humbly accepting, reverently and chearfully embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, and with thankfulneſs partaking of thoſe ſoul-benefits, conveyed and received in that Adminiſtration.</p>
               <div type="directions">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:173115:50"/>
                  <head>SABBATH.</head>
                  <p>SOme brief Rules for the better order and obſervation of the Lords Day, or Firſt Day Sabbath: Or if I may not call it a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath: I know no reaſon;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.12, 13.</note> But if the <hi>Jews</hi> were obliged to keep a Sabbath in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of a temporall delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, from temporall bondage, Chriſtians ſhould be much more bound to obſerve a day, as ſtrict as a Sabbath, in memoriall and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of their ſpirituall and eternall deliverance, from ſpirituall and eternall bondage. For doubtleſs Chriſtians are at great loſſes, becauſe of ſo much remiſneſs and want of ſtrictneſs in the Firſt Dayes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Firſt, Then let the Lords People be ſtirring betimes upon the Lords Day, called ſo by way of Eminency, having a greater work to do than on other days a work attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either with greater bleſſings, if religiouſly performed, or with greater damages, if neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected or miſimproved. Secondly, Let them make ſerious preparation, remembring whoſe ſervice it is, and into whoſe preſence they come; conſidering well what they go
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:173115:51"/>about, and how nearly it reſpects their eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Eſtate.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.1.</note> Thirdly, When they come into the Church Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, let them attend diligently, and behave themſelves reverently, and that before the Lord, with due and humble re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the adminiſtration and Majeſty of the Word. Fourthly, Let them with all watchfulneſs and holy indignation, ſtrive to avoid thoſe unſeemly and uncomely behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, tempers and geſtures of lukewarmneſs, coldneſs, drowſie, heavy, and dull and ſleepy carriages in Gods Divine ſervices, which is diſhonourable to their perſons, and alſo unprofitable to their ſouls. Fifthly, Let them Meditate upon what they have heard: For although the Lords People of the Congregationall way, are neceſſitated to take the moſt pains to hear the Word, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of diſtance of place; yet they have one priviledge, being improved may yeeld ſome advantage, having a fit opportunity to meditate as they go aſunder, or to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition as they walk together. Sixthly, To pray that the Preachers heart may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, and his tongue unlooſed, to ſpeak that which is ſound, profitable, and ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for their conditions; and when they have heard, to pray that the precious Word
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:173115:51"/>may be bleſſed and ſanctified to their ſouls, that by it they may be benefited and profited. Seventhly, To ſtir up each other to a better zeal, even to their firſt love, and to do their firſt works, and in a more ſtrict ſence and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act manner, more religiouſly to regard to keep and ſanctifie a Day to the Lord, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the whole Day in holy Exerciſe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Praying, Reading, Hearing, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring, or Meditating, and to lay aſide all ſuch talk and occaſions, as either reſpect State Matters, or any Secular Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and keep your ſelves that Day to Works of Piety, Mercy, Charity, and Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. If theſe Circumſtances were but religiouſly regarded and carefully obſerved; 1. Gods Honour would be more advanced, the Lords Day better improved, the peoples ſouls more edified, truth and profeſſion more credited, much needleſs diſcourſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, Satans deſign more weakened, their endeavours would be more certainly bleſſed, and their dayes work more fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded.</p>
                  <p>There is an order to be obſerved in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and diſcourſes, which being diſcreetly managed, may tend to profit and benefit. But beware of anger, which I may call the ſouls feaver, and cauſes the tongue to make
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:173115:52"/>digreſsion, and to exceed the bounds of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Let this Rule be taken; to ſpeak one by one, ſhort, materiall, and plain;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.26.</note> as <hi>He that bridles not his tongue his Religion is vain:</hi> So the well governing of the tongue, is a good degree of Religion, and deſerves the honour of a good commendation. One by one, to preſerve order; materiall, to have the weight of reaſon; plain, to help the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; ſhort, to help the memory. I have obſerved a diſtinction; a man may have wit and yet want wiſdome: Knowledge is the treaſure of the mind, but diſcretion is the key. I may call the tongue the hearts meſſenger, and as oft as it ſpeaks without me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation, goes without its errand, if not without reaſon. Some are ſo improvident in their words, and ſo extravagant of their underſtanding, that they can neither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it, nor know well to improve it, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately lay it out, that it returns them damage and not profit.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.28.</note> Every one hath a double leſſon to learn; one to know how to ſpeak, another to know when to hold his tongue. If ſuch Rules were put into practices, it would cauſe men to ſpeak to purpoſe, or elſe ſpare their ſpeeches: For <hi>a word
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:173115:52"/>ſpoken in its ſeaſon and order,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.11.</note> is like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Under your correction, I would tender my private opinion touching the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admisſion of penitent perſons, that have been under Excommunication. I have thought there is ſome obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be taken,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.24.</note> from the Lords receiving of the prodigal ſon, that ſome ſolemnity and form of ſpeech may be uſed to declare it, and to have as publick a conſent to his abſolution, as there was at his excluſion; and as the Parable ſpeaks, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them, and to rejoyce with them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were loſt, but now found, and wandered from the Lord, but are now return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And as the Apoſtle ſpeaks concerning the Inceſtuous <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthian;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 8.</note> he exhorts the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to conſider his remorſe and contriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to forgive him, comfort him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm their love to him. And there is good reaſon they ſhould give thanks to God for them, for hearing their prayers for them, for bleſſing the Ordinance executed againſt them, for recovering the finners out of the kingdome of Satan, and re-entering them into the priviledges of his Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:173115:53"/>
               <head>Fourthly, <hi>What Priviledges are to be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in Chriſts Congregation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt, We may ſay in this Caſe of Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks in his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs, Let none remove the Land-marks which our Forefathers or Elders have ſet;</hi> concerning Churches Rights and Priviledges, which we are to preſerve as a matter of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is part of Goſpell-Order and Church-Government. 1. Touching El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Superiors, they are honoured and priviledged with the Offices of Miniſters and Stewards, acknowledged by the Lord to be over his Family and Houſhold. 2. They have the priviledge to forbear working with their hands, eſpecially ſuch as labour in the publick Miniſtery, who are to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly unto ſuch things. 3. They have the priviledge to command others,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.15.</note> and others are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to obey them; provided all things be done according to Chriſts Laws given them. 4. They ought not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buked as others, but have the priviledge to be entreated as Fathers. 5. For their works ſake and Goſpell-labour, they ought to be
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:173115:53"/>much reſpected in love, and counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of double honour. 6. The Church ought not to receive an accuſation againſt them, under two or three witneſſes, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs becauſe the truth is ſo much concerned in their reputations, and repute and credit being the life of ſpirituall imployments. 7. 'Tis alſo their priviledge to be highly eſteemed, encouraged, and rewarded, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the Lord hath given direction and commanded.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Priviledges of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers. 1. As members ought to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Officers in their Priviledges, ſo Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ought in their places, to preſerve and ſecure the Priviledges of the members. The people of God have a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon right and equall propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety in the wiſdome, gifts,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21, 22.</note> and graces, which the Lord hath given to his Miniſters. For as <hi>Paul, Apollo,</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> are reckoned within the Saints Inventory, they are become obliged freely to disburſe ſpirituall Treaſures: By vertue of an intereſt the Saints may claim it as their right and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies. In this Caſe the People are proprietors,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.14.</note> and their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as debtors: For as the Lord hath been pleaſed to furniſh his Miniſters
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:173115:54"/>with heavenly riches and graces, ſo he hath commanded his Miniſtering Servants, to beſtow and improve ſuch gifts for the benefit of the Churches.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Another Priviledge as belongs of right to Church-members, is to have their part and equall ſhare in all Goſpel-advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and holy myſteries, even in that ſolemn and ſacred adminiſtration of participating, and having communion together in the Lords Supper, in the ſerious commemoration of the Lords Death and Paſsion.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28.</note> But let all that preſume to be Communicants at the Lords Table, examine themſelves, and make judgement firſt whether they diſcern the Lords Body, and ſo come worthily, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding his Reall, Myſticall, and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative Body.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, 'Tis the members Right and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge, to have their voice in electing their Overſeers and Officers that are to be ſet over them,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3, 5.</note> and alſo in the degrading or excluding any perſon in Office among them; upon which ſolemn occaſions they ought to be acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the matter may be freely and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally voted, that no members may complain of being diſpriviledged; and good reaſon for
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:173115:54"/>it, becauſe they are to be as Fathers to edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and feed them, and to provide their ſouls food, in order to their ſpirituall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and everlaſting good.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, 'Tis doubtleſs the Brethrens Priviledge, to have the knowledge of reciev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or excluding any member or members, into or out of communion with them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in doubtfull or difficult Caſes, becauſe they are to be or not to be mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame body,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4, 5.</note> and to have fellowſhip with them in the ſame holy myſtery; and if there be any ſin contracted, either in denying, recieving, detaining, or excluding any perſon, the evil may reflect upon the whole Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Another Priviledge is, If any Brother hath any injury offered him, or wrong done him, he ought to bring it legally to the Church, and there claim his Priviledge to be heard and relieved, and to call for juſtice to be executed. Then 'tis the Churches duty to proceed, and do them equity, conſonant to that good ancient Rule of doing as a man would be done by,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.7.</note> and that without delay and partiallity, that while we are complaining for want of juſtice from
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:173115:55"/>others, we may not neglect to do juſtice in the Churches.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Such among the Lords People as are juſtly poor, being of the body, have a right to be relieved in their outward neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: for as there is a right of propriety,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.3.</note> ſo there is a right of charity; 'tis the Lords Rent-charge, the Poors due, and the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es duty. There are ſome unjuſtly poor, who are either idle perſons, or led through their luſts into poverty; others by mans op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion are brought into penury; there are ſome impotent poor, ſo naturally; and there are the Lords poor, who become ſo through the conſequences of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, There is another Priviledge that belongs to Chriſtians: That if any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Party in a Congregation, ſhould veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judge and abſolutely believe, they were oppreſſed and over-ruled by the reſt of the Congregation, in any caſe or controverſie, that it amounts to high contention and diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8, 9, 10.</note> after all chriſtian and ſerious means uſed, he or they may make their humble appeal, to ſome other Church in the ſame Faith; and if the caſe be very
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:173115:55"/>weighty, then to have recourſe to ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 15.2.</note> that by all means ſchiſme may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord preſerved.</p>
               <p>To conclude theſe things: There are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rights, Immunities, and Priviledges, that of right appertain to Church-Members, that if any have a gift in Prayer,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10.</note> or by way of Exhortation to have his ſeaſonable time of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for the exerciſe of his gift, and to have encouragement in ſo good a work. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over; if any are under temptation, as wounding of ſpirit, ſickneſs of body, or any other afflictions, he may and ought to have recourſe to the Miniſters, and to ask coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and aſſiſtance of the Elders,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.14.</note> or to call for them to be their viſitants, and the Elders ought to attend them, in waiting upon their duties, by Prayers, Inſtruction, or any other ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherein Chriſts Miniſters are obliged, and become concerned, as they are ſpirituall guides, and Goſpel-Phyſitians. Thus we may both learn and diſcern the great Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, that pertain to ſuch as belong to Goſpel-Churches; to have intereſt in ſuch proviſions and advantages, and all within
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:173115:56"/>themſelves, under Chriſts government and dominion, and within their own limits and juriſdiction, where all rights and proprieties are equally to be diſtributed, their ſouls duely nouriſhed, their temptations conſidered, burdens removed, their bodies healed, their poverty ſupplied, their injuries redreſſed, and their priviledges maintained, and their cauſes heard, and contentions determined. Thus ought Chriſtians to have things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, in the ſpirituall Commonwealth and holy Nation, and to maintain a free fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and communion both in priviledges and ſufferings. The truth is, the charge of theſe things chiefly reſpects Officers, to whom the Church hath committed her power, and upon whom they have caſt the burden of their care, who ought as inſtruments in the name of Chriſt, with the Churches conſent, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the ſeverall parts and offices of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; and as they are intruſted by God, ſo they ought to act faithfull according to his Word; and as they ought not to exerciſe lordſhip, to uſurp authority, ſo they ought not to deface and diminiſh ought of Chriſts or his Churches power and dignity: For if our Lord died to enter the government, and our liberties and priviledges were purchaſed at ſo dear a rate, and now committed to the care
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:173115:56"/>of the Churches, there is a great obligation lyes upon the Congregation, to ſee that theſe things be carefully maintained, and conſtantly preſerved; and eſpecially ſuch as are in publick truſt, to improve their places, and diſcharge good conſciences, to be a juſt defence to all perſons in their ſpirituall rights and immunities, that there may be no juſt cauſe of complaints in all our ſtreets or bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Fifthly, <hi>What Diſorders are to be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, corrected, and removed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS when duties are put into the beſt form, they appear with the moſt beauty, ſo when the branches of impiety are ſet in order, they appear in their ugly ſhape of deformity. I will ſet ſome before you, which I believe are ſometimes found amongſt you, which are a diſhonour to Chriſtians, and are great diſturbances to the peace of the Churches; and theſe evils are both of omiſſion and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
               <p>Firſt, 'Tis found too much neglected by teachers and leaders, that the People are not taught, but are very ignorant in the orders and principles of true diſcipline and right go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:173115:57"/>
               <p> Secondly, When a man doth not prize and tender the unity and Peace of the Church as he ought, but ſhall inconſiderately and indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetly publiſh, and poſſibly endeavour to enforce a Principle upon the People, or a Practice upon a Perſon, before they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have ſufficiently tried and proved it, or the People or Perſon are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to bear it,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 16.12.</note> or made fit and capale to receive it, and ſo oft-times a diſturbance attends it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Another Diſorder which doth moſtly reſpect the Elders: That is, when diſorderly walkers who are known to live and continue in ſin, and the Church neglects her Duty in Diſcipline, not remembring all the time this ſin is unpuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2.</note> God is diſhonoured, their Duty neglected, the Truth reproached, the moſt religious griev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſcorners at Religion rejoyced, Gods appointed Ordinance to deſtroy the fleſh omitted, and the proper means neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, by which the ſinner ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Another Diſorder is, when the members of one Congregation, ſhall receive a member or members from another Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, without their knowledge or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:173115:57"/>or a letter of Recommendation from them to whom he or they did belong (except in any caſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary) by which diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders follow bad conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.1, 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 18.27.</note> for ſome perſons that think Chriſts Diſcipline too ſtraight, judging it little leſſe than tyranny, and their ſubjection to it little leſſe than ſlavery, when they are under reproof for ſome miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors will be ſhifting places and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving themſelves into Communion with other Churches.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Another diſorder is, when one member hath committed a treſpaſſe againſt another. The brother offended, which ought to treat with his brother offending betwixt them alone, and to have endeavored to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore his brother again, neither hath affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to regard his brother offending, or faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to reſpect the rule di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.20.</note> but takes his own ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular courſe, and whiſpers the matter till it comes to a breach, and ſo poſſibly at laſt becomes a general diſturbance in the Church, and endangers the diviſion of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Another diſorder is, when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation ſhall receive a matter between
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:173115:58"/>brother and brother into hearing, and not inquire of the orderly bringing it to the Congregation. If the matter be brought diſorderly to them, they by receiving it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty of diſorder with them; whereas they ought rather to reprove them and ſend them back to the Rule to do their duty, and refuſe to receive it before 'tis brought legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. If this was but duly obſerved many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and breaches would be prevented, and the Churches peace better preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Another diſorder is when the Church deals with any perſon or perſons for Miſdemeanor, either in matter of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, or for evill in converſation, or Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, or Schiſme or the like; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3, 4. Oft-times other members for private ends, either for Intereſt or Relation, will counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, aſſociate or ſide with them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them, and ſo many times make a diſtruction, if not a diviſion; ſuch are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to peace and contemners of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſuch ought to be ſpeedily noted as diſturbers timely reſtrained, and duly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
               <p>Eightly, Another diſorder touching the Church aſſembling upon the Lords day ſome as it were forſaking, others neglecting
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:173115:58"/>and give no cauſe of their ablenting; others come late, which doubtleſſe ought to be there at the Churches prayers, made in order to their Preparation, Sanctification and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection concerning the work of the Day, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.20. Some come when the Lords Market is half over; others with drowſineſs and fleepineſſe, as if they intended to make the Meeting-houſe their ſleeping place; and that time they pretend to improve in Gods ſervice, they ſinfully and waſtfully ſpend in the ſatisfying of the deſires of the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, Another diſorder is, when the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren abſent from Church-Communion in the Lords Supper, upon their own private O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, conceit, or imagination, to the offence of the Congregation, not giving any Cauſe or Reaſon to any for their ſo doing; make<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no account either to Church or Elder, whether the cauſe be in themſelves or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, not conſidering their loſſe and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage in their neglects, or their error in not committing their Caſe to cenſure.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, Another diſorder is, when the Church have diſcharged her duty againſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that have committed Iniquity. Many ſuch offenders will be their own Judges, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.12. and that in their own Cauſes,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:173115:59"/>and refuſe to ſubmit, if not contemn the Churches cenſures, not conſidering that they do preſumptuouſly and dangerouſly, and do as much as in them lyes to diſ-office Chriſt, diſ-priviledge the Church, and not diſcerning that they refuſed to be judged by the Law, but will be Judges themſelves and that of the Law.</p>
               <p>Eleventhly, Another diſorder is, when one Brother ſhall believe a report againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another brother, and that before he knows the truth of the matter, and poſſibly proceeds upon Rumors, Conjectures or Imaginations to paſſe ſentence of condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and that before any legall Trial or hearing, and ſo becomes guilty himſelf of the wrong that's done, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.13. in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diting ſuch reports againſt his brothers repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and to judge a matter before 'tis heard, is a fault of which a Chriſtian ought to be aſhamed.</p>
               <p>Twelfthly, Another diſorder or grievance is, when there is not an equall compliance together in matter of expence and publick charges, either touching the poor members or any other neceſſary disburſements; but 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13, 14. one is burthened, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is eaſed, ſome neglecting their duties, others not anſwerable to their abilities, and ſo the affairs and needfull occaſions of the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:173115:59"/>Churches, are not carried on by Equality, according to ability, and to anſwer to Rules of Equity.</p>
               <p>Thirteenthly, Another diſorder is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an occaſion againſt an Elder, and not under two or three witneſſes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.19. which is a diſorder in many places, not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Rule in that caſe provided, but upon every ſuſpition or light occaſion diſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected perſons will bring their Miniſters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute into queſtion.</p>
               <p>Fourthteenthly, Another diſorder is, when the Officers with the members appoint dayes of meeting upon neceſſary occaſions which concern all, and for the good of the whole, as days of Inſtruction, Diſcipline, Humiliation or Thanſgiving, or the like; and then Brethren ſhall upon every tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, indifferent and ſmall occaſion neglect ſuch appointments and uſefull meetings to their own loſſes and the diſcouragement of others.</p>
               <p>To conclude theſe things, God is not the Authour of ſuch confuſions, but a God of Order and the Authour of peace in all the Churches; But 'tis the Prince of miſ-rule, who by his ſubtill wiles ſtirs up ſuch inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to make breaches, and to break the Churches: and as I have drawn you a little
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:173115:60"/>Map to ſhew you the path of his deſigns; In like manner I would preſent to you as in a glaſſe, the nature of your adverſary by his Names:</p>
               <p n="1">1. He is called the god of this World, who blinds the minds of ſuch as believe not, leſt the light of the Goſpell ſhould ſhine unto them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He is called the Prince of the Air, that worketh and ruleth in the hearts of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of diſobedience.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Satan, who oppoſeth the Lord in his deſigns, and to pervert the Saints in their paths.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Devill, one that deviſeth miſchiefs, and by his wiles and darts to get advantages to over-rule and deſtroy the Saints.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Serpent, to ſhew his great policy, craft, and ſubtilties, in beguiling and betraying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent ſouls.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He is compared to a Lyon and a Dragon to ſhew his ſtrength, violence and cruelty, to fear, ſcatter and devour the Saints.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Belial,</hi> I may adde Tyrant, to draw perſons into Infidelity and Apoſtacie; a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant over them he takes captive, an oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, cruell and mercyleſſe, that Tyranizes over ſoul and conſcience.</p>
               <p>Thus I have given you the naming of the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:173115:60"/>Titles of your Adverſary, ſome hold forth his great policy, and ſome his great cruelty; I have done it to alarum you to take to your armour, to keep your watches, to defeat your enemy, and ſecure your ſouls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>6. <hi>Some branches of Injuſtice and Opppreſſion to be avoyded in the puniſhment of Sin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THe puniſhing of ſin is our great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. 1. What is ſin? 'Tis the tranſgreſſion of Gods Righteous Laws: and theſe evills are both of Omiſſion and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. In the execution of Diſcipline we are to endeavour the deſtruction of all ſin, and for our better knowledge and proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this deſign, we may enquire how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes a man may ſin. A man may ſin ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ways in the Commiſſion of ſin, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral wayes touching the puniſhment of ſin: 1. In the commiſſion of ſin, a man may actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſin in his own perſon. 2. A man may ſin by counſelling and abetting with another in ſin. 3. A man may ſin by countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and incouraging one that hath ſinned. 4. A man may ſin by not reſtoring his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that's overtaken in ſin. 5. A man may
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:173115:61"/>hate his brother and have fellowſhip with ſin by not reproving his ſin. 6. In a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact body all are guilty of another mans ſin that refuſe to joyn in the puniſhment of a ſinner. 7. And the Church may contract iniquity in doing Juſtice and not doing it throughly.</p>
               <p n="2">2. How may a man be guilty and ſin in puniſhing of ſin? <hi>Anſw.</hi> In the branches of in juſtice and Oppreſſion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To puniſh a man as an offender with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the breach of ſome Law is Injuſtice and Oppreſſion. 2. To neglect to puniſh an Offender that tranſgreſſes the Law, is a branch of Injuſtice. 3. To wreſt Judgement out of it's true Channell, and to turn Juſtice out of it's legall courſe, is another branch of Injuſtice. 4. To reſpect Perſons and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard Cauſes, ſo as to condemn the innocent and clear the guilty, 'tis Oppeſſion, In juffice, and an abomination. 5. To impoſe a leſſe penalty upon an offender then his offence deſerves, is another branch of Injuſtice. 6. To inffict a greater puniſhment upon a Treſpaſſer than the Law requires, is another branch of Injuſtice and Oppeſſion. 7. Not timely to relieve the Oppreſſed, and duly to acquit and diſcharge the Innocent man, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother high branch of Injuſtice and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:173115:61"/>To conclude this point in queſtion, this ſhews us what Juſtice is, by the rule of a contrary obſervation. To execute Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice timely, impartially, and thoroughly is true Juſtice according to Gods Law: having thus ſorted our materials and made our divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I proceed to Juſtice it ſelf in it's Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>7. <hi>Tho true Order of the Execution of Juſtice and Diſcipline.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>EXecution is the life of Governing; when Laws and Rules lye unexecuted, 'tis like Ingagements unperformed. Right Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline in it's execution carrieth a good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, It beats down evill deſigns, it gives Countenance to the beſt things, it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs the Nocent, and rejoyceth the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. It diſpleaſeth the Righteous God when ſuch as are placed, and be truſted <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.15. with the weighty imployment of Church-Government; and ſhall either not judge at all, or elſe in judgement are unjuſt and partial. To puniſh the Innocent that ought to be cleared, or to clear the Guilty that ought to be puniſhed. A man had need be juſt in diſcharging Conſcience in puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:173115:62"/>ſins, leſt he be found guilty of the bloud of periſhing ſouls: and when the Church of God ſhall aſſemble themſelves upon this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn occaſion;</p>
               <p n="1">1. Let the Word be ſounded like a Trumpet, that the people may be warned and informed into whoſe all-ſeeing preſence they come; and that God is preſent with them, and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth among them, to beget the people in an awfull fear and holy reverence of his ſacred Majeſty and Preſence; To remember the people by improving ſome words by way of charge, and to produce Commiſſions from Gods holy writing, and to let the people know they are properly concerned, legally returned, and ſolemnly ingaged, to take their places, and humbly to attend upon Gods ſervices, and to tell them the Lord hath betruſted us with Offices and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and furniſhed us with ſuch autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that we ſhould act like a holy Nation and ſpiritual Court, in all Juſtice and Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe all things are ſanctified by the Word and Prayer, let humble and fervent ſupplications be made to the God of Heaven to be counſell for you, and to prepare, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie and direct you in that ſerious matter undertaken by you, and that your part may
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:173115:62"/>be ſo done and performed on earth, That whatſoever ye bind or looſe may be done and confirmed in Heaven; <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.18. and as in all other Religious ſervices there ought to be good advice taken ſufficient tryal made before the exerciſe of action, much more in this caſe wherein we act for God, and muſt give an account to God in this matter: there had need to precede a Judgement of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration before the judgement of Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 1. To conſider, we muſt act in Chriſts Name and by vertue of his Authority, and that this action ought as it were to type out the laſt judgement, and to hold forth Chriſts Righteous Government. 2. To examine whether the matter be brought orderly, and the parties have proceeded legally. 3. To conſider the capacity of the perſon offending whether a member or a Officer; for although the Lord reſpects not Perſons, yet he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows ſome priviledge to Offices. 4. To enquire of the nature of the Offence, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more directly againſt God or man, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther publick or private. 5. To examine what provocations the offender had to it, and what deſign he had in it, whether ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or wilfully. Seventhly, Having found out the nature of the ſin then to have recourſe to the law that makes it a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:173115:63"/>Let the Law and the Offence be equally compared, and the penalty juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impoſed. 7. Let all proceedings be mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with compaſſion, that it may anſwer to the deſign of Heaven, the end to deſtroy the fleſh and to reſtore the offender out of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion. Having thus made preparation, proceed to probation and to the act of Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution; alſo remembring God is with you, and Judges of the judgement paſſed by you,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.1.</note> and that in a ſubordinate &amp; humble ſence: ye ought to hold forth the glory of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and that with all juſtneſſe, humble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and gravity repreſenting his dignity, mercy, purity, and ſeverity, and ſo to paſſe ſentence according as in Juſtice ye ſhall ſee cauſe, without delay or partiality, purged of all favour, prejudice, and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, without regard to cauſes, knowing faces or repecting perſons, as acting for God uprightly,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.17.</note> that it may be received and approved in the Court of Eternity.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Some further circumſtances to be obſerved in the proſecution of Church-Diſcipline, let be done and executed ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; not to ſuffer ſin to lye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy brother,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17.</note> or to infect the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:173115:63"/>ſpiritual body. A green ſore is ſooneſt healed, a diſeaſe taken new is eaſieſt cured; in like manner treſpaſſes or contentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Church-members taken timely, are beſt purged, appeaſed and reconciled.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Them that are Judges of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction are to be Counſellors to the offenders, eſpecially if they be ignorant perſons, not to daunt or ſurprize them or take quick advantages a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, but as we ought to act in the Lords Name, ſo to act in the Lords fear to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; to inſtruct them and convince them from the Scriptures, and ſhew them the Laws they have broken that judge them treſpaſſers, and condemns them for tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly. ſhew them their ſin in it's body and deformity; the ſad accidents and bad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences that attend ſin, and to make them ſenſible of their iniquity from the evidence of Scripture-teſtimony; ſay to the ſinner, Come ſee what you have done, look upon your ſin in it's aggravation, how ſerpent like it darts and ſtings every one, it reflects upon Gods honour, it darts Religion, ſtings the brethren, diſturbs your Inner-man, gives an occaſion of ſtumbling to the weak; in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, it daunts the well-wiſhers, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:173115:64"/>after Religion, and gives the enemies truth an occaſion of rejoycing.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, To learn to know the offenders deſign; for oft-times a deſign by an act in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, may be worſe than the action it ſelf committed: there may be Circumſtances depending, to be conſidered, by which the Act may be much mitegated or aggravated, as ignorance or wilfulneſſe, as in pretence of conſcience, or a deſign of diſturbance, as from a principle of Charity, or in a courſe of ſubtilty, the beſt of theſe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances will make no juſtification for any evill action, for that will be to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſin, but the better circumſtances are to have their mittegations in damages, (I mean in puniſhments) and the other their aggravations.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To obſerve the diſpoſition, capacity, and temper of the perſon, not to favour his ſin, but in order to gain an advantage upon the ſinner; ſome to ſave with compaſſion, ſome with fear, ſome with gentleneſſe, others with ſharpneſſei, always toſort, fit, and direct all admoniſhions, reproofs and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, as may beſt ſuit with the offenders diſpoſition, and the demerits of his ſin and tranſgreſſion.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, To take the moſt convenient
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:173115:64"/>ſeaſon, as I have ſaid; things done in their ſeaſon and order, are like apples of gold in pictures of ſilver, they are not only beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the action, but a diſadvantage to the enemies deſign; but beware leſt while ye are about to heal ſome breaches, you neither prevent nor diſturb your ſelves in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weighty and publick ſervices, and ſo let in Satan to make his advantages. For a man muſt have ſome reſpect in matters of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to three Eſtates, The honour of God, the quiet of Conſcience, and the peace of the Church. Thus I preſume to tender my Counſell and offer my Judgement and direction, eſpecially to ſuch as have any truſt and publick imployment over their brethren; for men of wiſdome, honeſty and ſufficiency are moſt ſenſible of the Office and buthen of the place, carefull of the Charge and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of the accounts they muſt make; like men of diſcretion let them well obſerve the nature of their Office and the worthineſſe of their places, and judge for God, according to the rule of his Word, with all juſtneſſe and gravity. As one obſerving the Judges ſit in the Judgement Seat; while they were grave and juſt he thought they were gods, but when they changed into ligheneſſe and fell into paſſion, he concluded they were but
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:173115:65"/>men. Let Chriſts Officers and Miniſters act gravely, juſtly, and diſcreetly; inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting themſelves and others in their ſeveral obligations, both as they are men and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians: As once a Governour of a Nation obſerved; ſaith he, I am King of Bodyes not of Souls, a Commander of men not of Conſcience. And as our Lord himſelf hath taught us to diſtinguiſh of duties, and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der every one their dues, and to owe nothing to any man but love. To honour our Lord Chriſt as the head of the Church, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect civil Magiſtrates as the politick fathers of our Countries. To conclude this point let me ſay to my brethren as once a Prince ſaid to his ſon, obſerving him to mind trifles; ſaid, Come my Son, leave trifles and mind the matters of the Kingdome: So I ſay to my brethren and every Chriſtian, to leave the trifles of this World, and mind the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Chriſts Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Peace and Unity is the great end I have here deſigned, and 'tis a deſign God hath greatly bleſſed. The Scholars in Chriſts Church ought to be Students for quietneſſe and peace in the Churches. The Lord hath not only commanded it, but he prefers Peace before any other Sacrafice.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.24.</note> 2. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:173115:65"/>his Diſciples to ſeek, peruſe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute Peace. 3. 'Tis further told us from the Lord, <hi>without Peace and Holneſſe no man ſhall ſee God.</hi> 4. Such as pray for Peace ſhall be bleſſed with Proſperity. 5. To the Councellors of Peace there ſhall be Joy. 6. The makers of Peace are honored by being called Gods poſterity. 7. Peace is a fruit of Gods ſpirit, and a Character of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdome. To haſt, God is the God of Peace, and Chriſt is a Prince of Peace, and the Kingdome of God is Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt. Thus are Saints to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Peace among them, and the Peace of God that paſſeth all underſtanding ſhall keep them.</p>
               <p>Thus are Chriſtians become concerned to endeavor to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of Peace; that is, What the Spirit of God hath united, formed and compacted together, either in reſpect of Fundamentals,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.3.</note> governing and perfecting Principles, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to maintain the ancient Form and true Pattern of ſound Doctrine and right Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline; That Truth and Peace may go hand in hand together, be conſtant Companions, and imbrace each other. You may pleaſe to learn a Leſſon from our experience in the
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:173115:66"/>Nation; When we are at Peace at home, then we ſee our Enemies are quiet abroad; when we diſturb and afflict each other by way of perſecution, it invites and embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens our enemies of other Nations, and in the midſt of home-bred contentions we hold o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen a door to let in forreign adverſaries. Let Chriſtians make ſpiritual application, who are within the borders of the holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to beware of Strife and Envy which makes way for the ſouls enemy, but to maintain Concord and Unity, which are as Bulwarks againſt the Adverſary, but let Union be made, and Charity increaſe, and have ſalt in your ſelves and be at Peace one with another; and as a concluſion, I would impoſe this one Obligation, as the late Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacy of a dying man; that the parties more chiefly concerned, may ſeriouſly apply it, and profitably improve it to Gods glory and their own felicity. 'Tis an Incumbent among Chriſtians; I wiſh it may never ceaſe, to keep the Unity of the ſpirit (and Truth) in the bond of Peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:173115:66"/>
               <head>Seventhly, and Laſtly. <hi>Some Directions given how to uphold and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Church-Government.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN order to the preſerving and ſupporting Church-Government, the matter will charge every mans concernment, both Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Members; It invites them to their duties, and obligeth them as Chriſtians to diſcharge good conſciences in all due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments, as they are under ſeveral ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations, and become concerned in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective places.</p>
               <p>And Firſt to my well beloved Brethren in the Lord, whom God hath called to high Offices, honored with great Endowments, and obliged in publick ſervices, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I do honor them in their reſpective places; Even thoſe Elders whom the Lord hath commiſſionated upon a more general account, who hath inlarged their miſſions into the Nations, and betruſted them with the care of the Churches. I will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to teach them becauſe I have more need to be taught by them; yet I would humbly take leave to be their Remembrancer, and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:173115:67"/>to intreat them as Fathers to obſerve their Goſpell-leſſons as they are directed to them by their ſeveral Appellations.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they are ſometimes called Angells, to hold forth Innocency and Purity.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Ambaſſadors in Chriſt ſtead, to perſonate his Majeſty and hold forth his glory in the World, ſent to treat with ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to ſtate the terms of Reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to engage their ſouls in affection with all bowels of Chriſtian compaſſion, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech them to be reconciled to God.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Meſſengers ſent out by the Churches upon the Lords meſſage,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.23, 24.</note> even upon the grand errand of publiſhing glad tidings. That match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and welcome news to poor ſinners;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.25.</note> even to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and proclaim a free tender of a crucified Chriſt unto a periſhing and loſt World; that Lamb of God that cleanſes ſouls by his precious bloud. Theſe are Inſtruments in Commiſſion from Chriſt, to unite ſtrangers to affect ſinners, to prepare members, to people the Churches.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, They are called Biſhops to ſhew they have a charge, and are Overſeers of the ſouls of ſuch as are Goſpell-profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:173115:67"/>and are to feed Chriſts flock, and to rule the Church of God, which he hath dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purchaſed with his own blood.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Ye are Miniſters to ſhew ye ought not to have dominion over the peoples Faith, neither to be Lords over Gods heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, but to be faithfull ſervants to Chriſt and the Churches.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Ye are called Rulers, to regulate Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, and to ſet in order things that are wanting in the Churches to ordain them Elders, and reform diſorders in the ſeveral Congregations.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Ye are called Stewards &amp; placed over the Lords Houſhold, to make proviſions, and to give them their ſpiritual portion of meat in due ſeaſons; which Office preſuppoſeth a high truſt, and ye muſt expect to give a faithfull and juſt account at laſt. Now that you may be guided aright to rule for God, I can do leſſe but pray and wiſh that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of Heaven may be upon you, and in you, even the bleſſings of ſoul and body, health and proſperity, but more eſpecially in the holy and high concerns of Eternity; That ye may have all increaſe of grace, fulneſſe of of peace, and at laſt your portion in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting ſtate of perfection, and in the mean time I freely wiſh ye may be all ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:173115:68"/>and richly furniſhed with all ſpiritual gifts and heavenly treaſures, and plentifully accommodated with the fulneſſe of the Holy Ghoſt; that ye may hold forth the Image of God and the glory of Chriſt in dignity, mercy, purity and ſeverity. To prize and praiſe the Godly and Pious, &amp; to diſclaim and condemn the Irreligious, and that ye may be duly directed and conſtantly protected by the goodneſs and providence of God, in and about the moſt ſacred acts of Religion, and in that ſerious and ponderous imployment of the Miniſtry, that the ſame Lord that hath commanded your ſervice, and given you au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, would be pleaſed to attend you with his preſence, and give you ſecurity, and that you may lay ſure foundations, and build a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Gods holy habitations, that ye may be Pious Examples to the believers both in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and Converſation, and worthy pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of Government in every Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; leaving behind you ſolemn and ſolid precidents of humility, fidelity, and gravity, with harmleſſe and diſcreet demeanors ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with holy policy, cincerity, and purity; that you may both conſtitute and conſolate Churches, unite Chriſtians, repair breaches, and eſtabliſh the Congregations Even to perfect faith and conduct ſouls to the everlaſting habitations</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:173115:68"/>
               <head>2. <hi>Concerning Elders appointed over parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Now direct my ſpeech to the Elders, charged with particular Congregations. My well-beloved Brethren; Conſidering my relation with you,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23.</note> and the great charge committed to you, and the great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count that's required of you, I could not well omit to adviſe, exhort, and entreat you, not ſo much to inſtruct you, as to remember you,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5.</note> to pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the worthineſs of your places, and the weightineſs of your obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: That ye are to ſerve Chriſt under his three fold Offices, in ſubordination to him; under the Offices of Prophet, Prieſt, and King. And 1. In order and honour to his Propheticall; to teach the people what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever God hath commanded you, and to with-hold nothing that is profitable for them, inſtructing them publickly, privately, and from houſe to houſe, declaring all the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of God, that ye may be pure from every mans bloud, and ſeaſonably, faithfully, and conſtantly, opening and preaching the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:173115:69"/>words and found doctrine, as ye have received it from the Apoſtles, according to the holy Scriptures, which was ſealed by God, and confirmed to them by miracles. In Chriſts name to teach and perſwade, and in much affection to exhort to duty, and by good inſtruction and a good pattern, to lead and guide the believers in acts and orders of Religion, and a well ordered converſation, obſerving ſeaſons and diſpenſations, having an eye to the peoples eſtate and conditions, diſcovering to every one their duty, with the benefits that attend it, and alſo acquainting them with the danger, upon the neglects and contempts of it. 2 Under his Prieſtly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, ye are to enquire of God for them, and to intercede him in their behalf, that they may have an evidence of their intereſt in Chriſts ſacrifice, and aſſurance of the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſin through him: That the Lord would pleaſe to encreaſe their graces, and that the bloud of Chriſt might purge them from all corruptions, and upon every occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in every condition, to commend them to God by ſupplication; and that they may be ſupported and comforted in the inner man; to offer the ſacrifice of thankſgiving unto God for them, for all benefits and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions freely received from him: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:173115:69"/>to inſtruct and acquaint them with the great bleſſings, that are preſented and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed by Chriſts Death and Paſſion, and to principle them in the great priviledge of his Interceſſion, and oft to celebrate the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of that memorable act, that ſo evidently preaches a crucified Chriſt; to teach them to diſcern the Lords Body, and to direct them how to communicate worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; then to call them to the Lords Supper, and endeavour to feaſt them with the Lords dainties, being communicants at the Lords Table, craving a bleſsing in every admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and a ſanctified uſe of every privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and bleſsing, rejoycing with them, and offering thankſgiving for them, for all bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits beſtowed upon them. 3. Under his Kingly Office, ye are to make known his Laws, and in his name to inſtruct them in the order and government of his houſe, and learn them to know how to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Church of God, that when they treſpaſs, they may not plead ignorance, and ſo oft-times matters are diſputed, in the mean time duties lye unperformed; but let Rulers require obediences according to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture directions, with authority, and yet in humility, to act and govern for the Lord, as men that are governed by the Lord, and ſo
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:173115:70"/>to rule and judge in all the Saints affairs, as them that muſt give an account to God them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; to counſell, warn, reprove, caſt out the impenitent and obſtinate, to reſtore the fallen, to ſtrengthen the weak, to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the humble, to abſolve the truly peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, not to bear the ſpirituall ſword in vain, even to do juſtice, and to ſhew mercy, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes deſigning to ſave the ſinners, but to deſtroy their iniquity: Let the exerciſe of diſcipline be well mixed with patience and compaſsion; teach them to have a filiall fear, and to ſtand in dread of him, who threatens to ſlay ſuch as will not have him raign over them. I will alſo ſet your Titles before you, and for my ſelf I pray and wiſh all ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bleſsing may attend you, in the diſcharge of the great work ye have to do. Theſe are your Names; Biſhops, Elders, Paſtors, Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Shepherds, Stewards, and Miniſters, all which ſpeak out the burden of your truſt, and charge ye have of ſouls. If one ſoul be of more value than the whole world, what an obligation hath he that hath the overſight, and muſt give an account of many ſouls. Look upon your Offices, and feel the weight of your burdens: Take good heed to your ſelves, to your doctrine, to your diſcipline, and to your converſation, and to all the flock
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:173115:70"/>over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeers, to feed and rule the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed dearly by his own bloud; taking care of them, not by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, but willingly, not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind, not as though ye were lords over Gods heritage, but enſamples to the flock: As Elders, to go before and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them; as Rulers, to command and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern them; as Paſtors, to feed and nouriſh them; Miniſters, not as lords, but to be ſervants to them; as Stewards, to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for them, and give an account of them; and as Shepherds, to watch over them. My dearly beloved, relations in the Lord; look upon that word of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> for your learning, and take it for your pattern, <hi>Chap.</hi> 40. <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>To feed the flock like a ſhepherd, to gather the lambs in the arms of tenderneſs, and into the boſome of your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and gently to entreat and guide ſuch as are with young:</hi> To lead them into green and ſound paſtures, and to water them in the ſprings of pure and wholſome waters, and faithfully to exerciſe all the parts of the office of a good ſhepherd; and as the wiſe man ſaith, <hi>To look well to the Flocks;</hi> even to take the number of them, the charge of them; to feed them; to aſſemble them; to rule them;
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:173115:71"/>to defend them from men-Wolves and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, that deſign to deceive and deſtroy their ſouls. To conclude; to act in all godly ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, fidelity, and gravity towards them, as men alwayes obliged to give an account for them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>3. <hi>Concerning the Deacons in Christs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>DEacons are Miniſters in Chriſts Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and are to be men of wiſdome, full of faith, and of a good report, ſound in the holy myſteries, and men of pure conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, whoſe quallifications are to be ſutable to the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8.</note> even to be grave and ſober, not greedy of filthy lucre; likewiſe muſt their wives be grave, ſober, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all things; to have well-ordered chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and well-governed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1.</note> they are the poor Saints overſeers, and are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the Churches treaſures; ye are Gods eminent ſervants, and are to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and ordained by election, prayer, and laying on of hands; your place is of weighty concernment, and doubtleſs ye
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:173115:71"/>ought to be helps and aſſiſtants in govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and as inſtruments in offices, to ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill Gods gracious promiſes: In a ſence, to be fathers to the fatherleſs, and busbands to widdows, and as it were to be eyes to the blind, and feet to the lame, and as advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates for the poor ſaints. And as Elders are ſet over the Lords people, more directly and properly in ſpirituall things, and ſoul-mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo Deacons are to wait and ſerve at the Lords Tables, and to make due proviſions for the poors externall and bodily concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, in reſpect of their Deaconſhip, and yet may be uſefull to ſouls, as they may be gifted diſciples. In this we may behold Gods wonderfull providence and goodneſs, in appointing Offices and Officers, to make ſutable proviſions for his peoples ſouls and bodies, and that at all times, and in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. And as this is an Office of eminency and neceſſity, ſo 'tis accompanied with great care and much difficulty; to carry an even hand, and a faithfull heart, between the Churches poverty, and the poors neceſsity. And doubtleſs as Elders are to admoniſh and reprove in neglects, touching duties of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Piety, which are more ſpirituall, in like manner it doth concern Deacons to exhort and reprove, in matters that reſpect
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:173115:72"/>the poors ou ward neceſsity temporall. Let them remember they are inſtruments by the Lords order, to take the care and over-ſight of the Lords poor; for where there is an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, without doubt there's power to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, that things may be done by equallity, according to every mans ſtate and abillity; not one burthened and another eaſed. And having ſo good a cauſe to plead, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the poor and needy, it well becomes you to take boldneſs to blame ſuch, as detain from the poor their right of charity. My well beloved Brethren, I wiſh and pray ye may be bleſſed from heaven with ſutable gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſpirituall accommodations, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of your duties and great obligations; that as the Lord hath honoured you with a truſt in your Offices, ſo you may faithfully endeavour to honour God in your reſpective places, acting in all fidelity, confonant to the prime Rules of juſtice and equall dealings, as men obliged to give an account to God and the Churches. 1. Let them be to the poor as fathers, in reſpect of compaſsion, as men naturally ſympathizing with them in their low condition. 2. Give them good advice and counſell, to be induſtrious in their callings, and provident in their expences, that they may not bring any unneceſſary charges, and
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:173115:72"/>unjuſt burdens, upon the Congregations. 3. If they be able, and refuſe to work, then to admoniſh them. The Apoſtle is ſharp in this caſe, and ſaith, <hi>If any would not work in their common imployments, neither ſhould he cat of the Churches charges.</hi> Laſtly, They are in the place of fathers, to enquire into their conditions, leſt any lye under temptations, for want of outward ſupplies, and according to the juſtneſs of their neceſsity, and equall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their poverty, to relieve them, and prepare portions for them, ſutable to their conditions; even to feed the hungry, cloath the naked, viſit the ſick, houſe the harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs: This hath the repute of pure Religion, even to viſit the fatherleſs and widdows in their affliction. Let all be done according to thoſe good laws of piety, equity, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and of doing as a man would be done by: And as the burden of the Office is caſt upon you, ſee that you diſcharge your truſt faithfully. And in all this the Deacons are to be aſsiſted, and enabled by the Churches collections, diſtributions, and communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>Now what power and order there ought to be among Officers themſelves; what power the Meſſengers have over the Elders; what power the Elders have over the Deacons;
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:173115:73"/>what power the Deacons have over the Members, which doubtleſs there is ſome or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and that among ſuch as have power, even among Governours as well as in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments: But I ſhall refer this difficult point to ſome abler head, and more skilfull hand, to determine it. But thus I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude to wiſh; That as God hath called you to places of order and honour here, ſo you may be rewarded and crowned with dignities and honour hereafter. To end this point, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that both Officers and Members may learn a lecture for government and orders, from the Firmaments, and by the Sun, Moon, and Stars: They be like the Sun for light and heat; like the Moon for declaring ſeaſons, and conſtancy in circuit; and like the Stars, for holding on their courſe, and keeping or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and place. Now if you think theſe few lines, eſpecially ſpoken to Officers, be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of acceptation, and may deſerve the place of counſell and direction, conſider of them, and the Lord encreaſe all your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and underſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:173115:73"/>
               <head>4. <hi>Concerning the duties of Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to their Officers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MEmbers of Churches as they ſtand in relation to their Officers it concerns them to acquaint themſelves with Scripture-obligations, what is required of them in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion to Officers laws and orders, that they may clearly know, and chearfully do, what reſpect them on their part, to preſerve true order, and ſupport right govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Firſt, 'Tis the mind and alſo command of God, that Chriſtians ſhould obey ſuch over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers, as are ſet over them in the Lord, and whoſoever refuſes to be obedient, reſiſt Gods appointment, alwayes provided, they exerciſe rule according to the direction of his Word, not to their perſons as they are men, but as they are the Embaſſadors and Stewards of Chriſt, for they act by vertue of the Lords Commiſsions; and 'tis written, the holy Ghoſt appoints overſeers, and 'tis the Lords meſſage they are upon,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> and the Lords work they labour in, and God is a God of order, and not of confuſion, who hath ordained go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:173115:74"/>and required your ſubjection Officers rule for him, therefore members ought to ſubmit to them, for the Lords ſake, for conſcience ſake, for the Goſpels ſake, and your own ſouls ſake, <hi>That they which watch for your ſouls, may give an account with joy,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5 5.</note> and not with grief, for that will be unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for you;</hi> for indeed your obedience is not to man but to God. My dearly beloved Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I beſeech you beware in this weighty matter, for there is no fin in the world which the Lord hath puniſhed with greater ſeverity, than he hath diſobedience to Authority; neither was it ever heard that the earth open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her mouth wide, to ſwallow up man, as it did <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> for their reſiſtance and contempt to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Jude</hi> do both aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate this crime, as a grand tranſgreſſion, for <hi>To ſpeak evil of dignities, and to deſpiſe domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> one of our ancient Fathers, in his Epiſtle to the ſcattered Chriſtians, he is a very full Author, and that to this very matter, who pleads for ſubmiſſion to Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, both in Nation, Church, and Family: firſt to honour God, and to obey ſuch as are appointed by him; to ſubmit to ſupreme Governours, and ſuch as are ſent by them;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:173115:74"/>wives are to be in ſubjection to their own husbands; ſervants are to be ſubject to their maſters, not only to the courteous and good, but alſo to the diſcourteous and froward; and this obedience muſt be for the Lords ſake, alwayes to make true diſtinctions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſpirituall and temporall ſervices, to give to man their dues and duties, and to God his honour and praiſes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And as the Lord hath required ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to his Miniſters, ſo he hath enjoyned his people to honour them that rule over them,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12, 13.</note> and to know ſuch as labour among them, and admoniſh them, and to count ſuch worthy of high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for their works ſake,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.29.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God himſelf hath digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied them, and hath commanded the Saints highly to eſteem them. St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives this high commendations of the faithfull and painfull Elder, that he deſerves the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of double honour; and becauſe their work is labourious and dangerous, the people ought to countenance them by being courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. The meaneſt inſtrument imployed by the Lord in his ſervice, the Saints ought to receive, and accept with readineſs and chearfulneſs. Doubtleſs he that loves God,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:173115:75"/>his truth, order, and ordinances, will natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally reſpect ſuch as act in them as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: I ſpeak not of needleſs cuſtomes, or idolizing perſons, but to honour God in them, and to honour God by them, and to reverence them, becauſe the image of God is upon them; for God was angry with the <hi>Jews,</hi> becauſe they deſpiſed his meſſengers, and it mounted their ſins, untill there was no more remedies. And to ſome the Lord ſaith in the <hi>Lamentations,</hi> He would divide them, and no more regard them, becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected not their Teachers, nor reverenced the face of the Elders: For what kindneſſes or injuries are done to them, the Lord takes it as done to him; and Chriſtians are to hold ſuch in repute, and to endeavour as much as they may to preſerve their credit, for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-reputation is the life of ſpirituall tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: Therefore none are to receive an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation againſt an Elder, under two or three witneſſes, becauſe in defaming an Elder, the truth ſuffers treble damages; but the ſame and eminency of Chriſts Miniſters, is a glory to Chriſt, and an honour to his Churches.</p>
               <p n="6">6. 'Tis a duty incumbent, and a matter of high concernment, to preſent humble and fervent prayers, for ſuch as are called to be
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:173115:75"/>Goſpel-governours, that they may rule for God agreeable to his counſell, contained in his Word, with all juſtice and righteouſneſs, towards all degrees of perſons; and to pray, being earneſt, that God would ſend more faithfull labourers into his harveſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.38.</note> that the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant world may be converted, and that there might be daily added unto the Church of God, ſuch as ſhould be ſaved. And as for thoſe inſtruments the Lord hath already ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, to intercede him that he would be graciouſly pleaſed, to furniſh them with wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, enrich them with graces and ſpirituall treaſures, and beſtow upon them the ſpirit of revelation; to ask for ſpirituall boldneſs, and for the gift of utterance, and that they may be ſpirited againſt all allurements and diſcouragements, that neither the fear of men, nor the cares of this world, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them or divide them from their duties in Gods ſervices, but that they may ſpeak as they ought to ſpeak, with courage and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs: And to beg of God that he would pleaſe to give them right principles of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and to honour them with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of diſcerning and judgment; and as the Apoſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.1.</note> Pray for us; that the Goſpel may
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:173115:76"/>have a free courſe, and run and be glorified, and the Goſpel-Miniſters preſerved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered: For as we are to pray and give thanks for Kings, and all that are in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that we may live a peaceable life under them, ſo we ought to make prayers and ſupplications, for all ſpirituall Guiders and Governours, that the Goſpell may be advanced by them. Let all Chriſtians know, 'tis a materiall duty in the ſeverall Congregations, to aſſiſt the Preachers of the Word, by their fervent and conſtant ſupplications; and that giving of thanks be returned, and duely rendred unto God, for all thoſe gifts and graces he hath beſtowed on them, and for the bleſſing of God you enjoy by them, and for all the experiences they have enjoyed through Gods goodneſs to them, the admirable proviſions made for them, and his wonderfull providences over them, and for the unexpected benefit you reap by the enjoyments of your Miniſters, and that they are not yet removed into cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. Let theſe things be freely owned, and ſenſibly and thankfully acknowledged, and Gods due praiſes ſutably and conſtantly rendred; and if our duties and the Lords due Rents be ſeaſonably diſcharged, it may be our priviledges may be enlarged, our
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:173115:76"/>ſpirituall immunities encreaſed, our gifts and graces augmented, and our liberties and freedomes eſtabliſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>7. Laſtly, <hi>Touching Gods Ordinance, that reſpects his Miniſters Maintenance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Firſt, The Church of Chriſt ought to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Gods Ordinance, to aſſiſt and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Goſpel-Miniſters with a Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maintenance, that the Goſpell may not ſtand at their door, and the obſtruction and neglect of this good work, may not be charged upon their ſcore. And becauſe this point may ſeem the moſt ſtrange, I would borrow the more time to ſpeak more at large. In my proſecution I would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this method following, to diſtinguiſh of it: What it is, and what it is not. 1. What it is not: 'Tis not a compelled and forced maintenance, no otherwiſe than the Word of God compelleth. 2. Chriſts Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ought not to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſo their end of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.17</note> as no pay no preach. 3. They ought not to expect much leſs to extort from poor men, to whom they had more need to give than receive. 4. Upon the neglect and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:173115:77"/>none-payment,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12, 14.</note> there's no rule in the Goſpell to inflict bodily puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What Goſpel-maintenance is: 'Tis a free communicating by him that is taught in the Word,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</note> to him that teacheth in all good things: he that preacheth the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14, 11.</note> and ſuch as miniſter ſpirituall things to the people, the people ought to miniſter tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things to them. 'Tis due by divine right; the Lord hath ordained it and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it; his eminent ſervants have plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it and alſo received it; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of his priviledges, ſaith, he hath power to forbear working; and the ſame Apoſtle, labouring with his hands, reckons it among the reſt of his afflictions, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns <hi>Timothy</hi> to give himſelf wholly to the Miniſtry: And although they may not preach for lucre, yet they ought to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in neceſſities, if not with convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; and though they may not expect great revenues and augmentations, yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they ought to be ſo remembred, as to prevent decayes and poverties, that ſo the
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:173115:77"/>Miniſtry may be preſerved from reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; ſome having ſpent a great part of their outward ſubſtance, ſome their all, and ſome more than all, which is a temptation to Miniſters, and a diſhonour to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Arguments alledged for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of it. As the Goſpel-Miniſters are reckoned within the Saints Inventory, and their graces the peoples by legacy, ſo Chriſts Miniſters have a right of propriety in the peoples common treaſury. The Lord hath given his own precept for it, and hath charged his Church in truſt to perform it; the neglect is not only the breach of a Law, and omiſſion of duty, but it highly reflects upon the Lords honour and dignity, who hath deſigned all things to be acted freely; God loved us freely; Chriſt dyed freely; this good news is to be preached freely; and ſuch as are taught ought to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate freely. Every mans ſervants are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſome recompence for their labours; all differing perſwaſions do much counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance their Miniſters, and ſhall ours want their due encouragements; and this is no more in ſubſtance, than what was confeſt and ſubſcribed in the Confeſſion of Faith, 1660, If a man neglect his own private oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:173115:78"/>and for the good of others adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture himſelf into eminent dangers, 'tis rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable he ſhould be accommodated from the peoples treaſures: It neither conſiſts with Religion nor common reaſon, that a man in this caſe ſhould bear his own burden, expend his own particular ſubſtance, upon the publick cauſe and generall occaſion; as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>No man goes to warfare at his own charges;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.</note> as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Who is there among you that would ſhut the doors for nought:</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not ſay, they that preach the Goſpell may live, but ſhould or ought to live of the Goſpell. He further reaſons the caſe from naturall civil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and common equity, to convince the <hi>Corinthians</hi> of the Goſpel-Miniſters mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and although he refuſed to take of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> becauſe of the falſe teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, yet he tells them again, he robbed other Churches to do their ſervices: And he ſaith elſewhere, they that are imployed in Goſpel-labour, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted worthy of double honour;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17, 18.</note> the workman is worthy of his meat, and the labourer of his wages: And though they labour not ſo much with their hands, yet they labour
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:173115:78"/>with their brains, and undertake and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo great difficulties; they are ſet not only to preach, but defend the Goſpell; rulers of a holy Nation; ſtewards of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Court; warriers againſt ſpirituall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries; planters in the Lords Vineyard; feeders of his Flock; governours of his ſhips; phyſitians of his patients; plowers of his earth; ſowers of his ſeed; labourers in his harveſt; and as threſhers in his barn: and all for ſpirituall proviſion for the nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment of ſouls, even for their welfare, ſafety, and preſent profit, and to guide and conduct them to their eternall prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The neceſſity of it. In the former buildings ſome laid the foundations, other were overſeers of the work, and ſome to bear burdens. There is a neceſſity the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell ſhould be preached, and the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Gods ſpirituall houſe laid, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers appointed, and the work preſerved, and others to help to bear the burdens:
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.16.</note> For if the Goſpell be neglected, there is a woe pronounced; ſo that in this Goſpell-work there are inſtruments and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtants. Then let all ponder and ſeriouſly conſider, that are become concerned and
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:173115:79"/>are obliged in this weighty matter; for ſome betake themſelves to farming, that are appointed to publick preaching, and cannot go out upon the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, becauſe of the preſſing cares of family-neceſſity; when as the Apoſtle ſaith, No man that warreth entan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles himſelf with the affairs of this life:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4.</note> And if the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles thought it not reaſon and meet to leave the Word and Prayer, to ſerve tables, an office in the Churches, much more is it unreaſonable for Goſpel Preachers to leave the work, to follow worldly occaſions. I may ſay ſome have robbed their own fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies to ſpend their time in the Churches ſervices; for much is already known, and much more is feared and foreſeen, of the great inconveniencies that attend this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as naturall conſequences.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The bad and ſad effects that accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the neglect of it. 'Tis to be feared that ſome that have been eminent in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, have declined the way of truth and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, being under temptations, for want of ſupplyes neceſſary. In the former diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the people detained the Lords ſervants right, the Lord charged them that they robbed him, and for that he would
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:173115:79"/>come as a ſwift witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 8.3.</note> If the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith 'tis even ſo in the duty, we may juſtly fear it may be even ſo in the penalty. If the keeping back the labourers wages,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.4.</note> cryes in the ears of the Lord of Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, ſhall not we fear if we neglect ſuch as faithfully and painfully labour in the Word and Miniſtry. My dearly beloved Brethren, let theſe things be pondered; I do not charge you but warn you, and in diſcharge of my own duty, and to give you notice to eſcape the danger of the penalty; for there is a neglect, and it will be charged ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; let every man do his duty according to his meaſure. This then is the great ſtrait, that either the work of the Lord muſt be neglected, or that which properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to wife and children, muſt be waſted. 'Tis not the mind, neither is it for Gods honour, that one ſervant ſhould be oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and another eaſed; and whether the Lord may not reckon for eſtates decayed, bodies waſted, ſpirits and bloud ſpent and not regarded, as well as conſciences oppreſt and bodies deſtroyed. This is the ſtrait be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt two, either to neglect the worthy work of the Goſpell, or elſe to be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:173115:80"/>of being reputed worſe than an Infidell. Moreover beſides all this; 'tis more than hard to obtain a ſucceſſion of Miniſters, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis foreſeen and known the Church makes no proviſions: And theſe things I have not only by intelligence, but by ſad and known experience.</p>
               <p n="6">6. There are ſome circumſtances to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, touching and relating to this matter. Let none be miſtaken or deceived, as to think that I plead for parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular perſons,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.17.</note> or private intereſt; not that I deſire a gift, or that it ſhould be ſo done to me: For I thought I might ſpeak the more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe I have not been chargeable to any, no otherwiſe than in common enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments; nay if need be I can give teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that I have refuſed when it hath been tendred me. But I can aſſign more publick and better ends; as the preaching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, the converſion of ſinners,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.9.</note> the conſtituting and confirming of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, the convincing and improving gainſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, the uniting Chriſtians, the repairing breaches, and the eſtabliſhing and ſetting in order the Congregations, and more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that fruit might abound upon the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:173115:80"/>Lords peoples account. There may be times and occaſions that a man may abate of his due, and remit of his right: Some cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances may require it, where the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have not ability, and when the Lords people may be in diſtreſs and neceſſity, whoſe conditions may call for more than ordinary ſupplyes: Such circumſtances ought to be obſerved, notwithſtanding it be a duty commanded. I ſpeak not this that the Lords people ſhould be burdened, nor any particular mans deſire anſwered, but that every mans duty and conſcience may be diſcharged, the Goſpell preached, Miniſters encouraged, and the work of God furthered and advanced.</p>
               <p n="7">7. An Exhortation to diſcharge your du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in theſe weighty buſineſſes. God is not mocked; what a man ſowes that he ſhall reap. Let not me be thought tedious, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let this work be counted wearineſs: There is ſuch great need the Goſpell ſhould be ſpread, and ſuch great complaints for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, moves and preſſes me to be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to perſwade to anſwer their expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Lords requirements. 1. Let the Lords Miniſters ſee there be no default and neglect in them,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.2.</note> neither to have a covetous deſire
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:173115:81"/>after gain and filthy lucre; but freely to go out in the Lords name upon the Lords work, and chearfully caſt themſelves upon the Lords promiſes and providences, for their ſucceſs and ſecurity. And let the Churches ſee that they neglect not their duty, as helps and aſſiſtants to them in the Miniſtry; for coyn and treaſure is the ſinews of war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare. Let every one help as he hath receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not one eaſed, and another over-burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.13, 14.</note> Let this law be the rule and order, as you would have another do to you, do you in like manner to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And whoſe heart the Lord hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged towards this needfull work, let it be done chearfully and in charity, agreeable to principles of equallity, anſwerable to abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and conſonant to rules of equity, for all receits muſt be accounted, for we are but Stewards of that we are poſſeſt, for the earth is the Lords and all things therein, for we our ſelves are not our own, neither is any of our ſubſtance or coyn; bodies, goods, and ſpirits, are to glorifie him, for we are but tenants to the immortall and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Lord, when he calls for our ſelves or ſubſtance to ſerve him, we ought to render up all to him; for every Chriſtian
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:173115:81"/>man the Lord hath made ſtewards of a worldly poſſeſſion, ſtands obliged with this Rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, by vertue of Religion; beſides thoſe of his family, to communicate to the poor ſaints, and ſuch as labour in the Miniſtry. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved brethren, I can do no leſs but caution you againſt covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5.</note> which is ſo deſtructive to pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and which the Apoſtle calls Idolatry, which eſpecially conſiſts of two generall parts, either an unlawfull getting and poſſeſſing, or an unjuſt with-holding and detaining that from another, of which he is the true owner, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when his neceſſity calls for it ſpeedily. Beware then of detaining any dues from the Lord when he calls for it, even that which he hath reſerved and excepted for the poor Saints, and his miniſtring ſervants, which belongs to them, as given from the Lord, and proved to be their right by his Word. My dearly belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed brethren, let not me be thought the worſe, although I preſent you with this diſcourſe. I hope you will excuſe and pardon my boldneſs and plainneſs, becauſe 'tis a publick good, and an univerſall cauſe, even a deſign to advance the honour of God, and for poor ſouls ſpiritual and eternall good. Let every man help as he hath received, and as he ſtands obliged, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be in reſpect of ſpiritualls or temporalls:
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:173115:82"/>The wiſe man with his wiſdome; the gifted man by exhortation; the rich man with his treaſures; all help together by their hearty and fervent prayers. He that giveth let him do it with ſingleneſs; he that ruleth, with dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; and he that ſheweth mercy, with chearfullneſs, for the Lord loves a chearfull giver.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8.</note> Take one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon more: When many ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are ſet to bear a heavy weight, it cauſes each mans burden to become very light; and as Goſpell Preachers ought to be tender in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing chargeable to the Churches, ſo ought Churches not to make the Goſpell burdenſome to the Preachers. Let Chriſtians comply and agree together, as <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Abiſhai</hi> did, to maintain a temporall warre; <hi>Joab</hi> ſaid to his brother, <hi>If the enemy be too ſtrong for me, thou ſhalt help me, if he be too ſtrong for thee, I will help thee:</hi> So ought brethren to do who are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in the cauſe of Chriſt, to aſſiſt each other in all ſpirituall combats, and to help to bear one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2.</note> for this is to fulfill the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Law of Chriſt. But to be ſhort and plain; my brethren, I am not without my fear, leſt we ſhould provoke the Lords diſpleaſure, even to blaſt our bleſſings, and diſpoſſeſs us of our freedomes, becauſe he hath done ſo much for
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:173115:82"/>us, and we have done ſo little for others; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubject to forget we ought to be lights to the world,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.13, 14.</note> and ſalt to the earth; and becauſe we have not ſuch ſympathizing diſpoſitions, and compaſſionate hearts, to pitty the dark condition of the world, and ignorant eſtate of poor ſinners, even while we hear them calling upon us in ſeverall places, as it were complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for want, and calling out for help, and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing relief for their poor ſouls. Let Churches therefore ſet out their lights and every one add their helps, ſome as actuall inſtruments, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as inſtrumentall aſſiſtants, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell may be publiſhed, unregenerate perſons converted, and hungry and thirſty ſouls may be ſupplyed and refreſhed. I will take leave to adde one thing more which I have obſerved: That our Chriſtian relations come ſhort of ſome other perſwaſions, who when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this world poſſeſt of temporall wealth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath part to ſome pious and publick ſervices; and this part of their charity as it were perfumes their memory, and like <hi>Abels</hi> faith and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice will ſpeak and (in a ſence) preach after a man dyes. If ye believe this concerns you, conſider what I ſay, and the Lord give you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in all things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object. But we are unable and cannot give be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:173115:83"/>of our families, and many other expences, payments, and charges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The husbandman that laboureth, muſt firſt be partaker and receive of the fruits. Ought not Chriſtians firſt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the kingdome of God,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6.</note> and pay their firſt fruits to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Lord. Let the Objection be thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved; that the intereſt of Chriſt and the cauſe of ſouls ſhall be firſt preferred. If you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give talents, yet caſt in your mites into the common treaſury, for it will be accepted according to what a man hath, if it be done chearfully. Take heed my brethren of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting or murmuring at free disburſing to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell-Preaching; he that thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends his treaſure lends to the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.10.</note> and the Lord will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get but requite them an hundred fold. Who knows but the Lord intends to tempt you to prove him, as in the Prophet <hi>Malachies</hi> time, when he ſaid, <hi>If you will bring meat into my ſtore-houſe, ſee if I will not open the windows of heaven, and pour you out bleſſings without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that there ſhall not be room enough to receive it.</hi> Who knows but that for a little expended, there may be much received: But I leave it to the wiſe for them to apply and Goſpellize.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16.</note> 
                  <hi>To do good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:173115:83"/>forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices God is well pleaſed,</hi> and the ſacrificer ſhall be well rewarded.</p>
               <p>And if in this ſmall Tract any thing that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to this preſent Subject, hath either ſlipt my memory, or hath been above my capacity, that hath or may ariſe as a queſtion in Chriſts Congregation, I not knowing what particular thing, I will give this generall reſolution: That when two things or two wayes ſhall ariſe in debate, and one of them is doubtfull and the other is ſafe, then in ſuch a caſe, to chuſe the way that is ſafe, alwayes deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and purſuing after the things that make for peace.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I have briefly declared and freely ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered my judgement and opinion, in my own plain ſtile, and according to my own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: It hath alſo been my care to avoid occaſions of offences and grounds of diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and withall I have endeavoured to free my ſelf from detraction and derogation of any mans perſon, office, or perſwaſion, it being much contrary to my diſpoſition; yet this I know, what of truth I have written, bears its oppoſition to all that oppoſe it, whether they ſpeak evill of it, or come ſhort of it, or act contrary to it, or depart from it, it ſtands in its own defence. If yet notwithſtanding my
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:173115:84"/>reſpect to diſſenting and differing brethren, and tenderneſs to others, any man ſhall carp and be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16.</note> their end will be the better diſcovered; let them know we have no ſuch cuſtome, nor the Churches of God.</p>
               <p>To conclude all, I give this Admonition, Caution, and Encouragement, touching the exerciſe of right diſcipline and righteous go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; that ye call to memory the danger of the curſe, chreatned againſt ſuch as do the work of the Lord negligently, or deceitfully, and ſloathfully, witneſs old <hi>Ely,</hi> for reproving too lightly, and <hi>Saul</hi> for executing judgement deceitfully, and that wicked ſloathfull perſon, who neglected to improve his talent faithfully, for his negligence and remiſneſs, is ſencenced to be bound hand and foot, and caſt into utter darkneſs.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.26, 30.</note> Moreover <hi>Judas</hi> for deceit and treachery, and <hi>Demas</hi> for turning from the truth to idolatry: Beſides in the time of the Prophet <hi>Malachy,</hi> the Lord blames the people for dealing deceitfully, detaining from his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants their right of propriety, by which his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſhould be performed, his ſervants main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and the poor relieved: The Lord is pleaſed to define the ſin, and calls it robbery and injuſtice, he repayes the evill with a curſe
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:173115:84"/>of penury. And as all Scripture is recorded for our learning and inſtruction, ſo theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidents of miſcarriages and puniſhments, are become our premonitions and warnings, that by preventing the ſins, we may clearly eſcape the puniſhments. Thus much be ſpoken touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Caution and Admonition.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, A word of Encouragement, and ſo I have done: I am of St. <hi>Peters</hi> perſwaſion, to put you in remembrance of theſe things, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ye know them, and be eſtabliſhed in them; but to obſerve the ſpeciall notice the Lord takes, and countenance he manifeſts, to ſuch as are juſt and righteous, as <hi>Noah, Lot,</hi> and <hi>Phineas, Caleb, Joſhua,</hi> and many others, who for their integrity, fidelity, and ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, are bleſt with ſpeciall ſecurity, that while others fall under judgement and miſery, as a demonſtration, the Lord records their names, commends their actions, ſecures their perſons, and comprehends in the bleſſing their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and families. The Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpeaking in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of <hi>Joſiah</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> ſaid thus of him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.15, 16.</note> that he did execute judgement and juſtice, and then it was well with him; this is rightly to know God; <hi>Was not this to know me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> Theſe that were men of juſtice and faithfulneſs, the Lord
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:173115:85"/>counts it unto them for righteouſneſs. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> was a righteous man, and faithfull and juſt in reproving ſin, and ſo obtained this commendation to be called a juſt and holy man. Alſo the Lord was pleaſed greatly to honour <hi>Abraham,</hi> in making him privy to his deſign of juſtice upon <hi>Sodom,</hi> and admits him to parle touching their deſtruction; the Lord gives this character of him, that he will command his children and his houſhold after him,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.</note> and like a man of government, to keep the way of the Lord, to do juſtice and judgement. The Lord doth ſo highly account and ſo much delight in truth and judgement, that if there were but one man found in the City <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.1.</note> to ſeek for it, and in the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it, notwithſtanding a wicked City, he would pardon it. The Lord takes ſuch pleaſure in juſtice, that he prefers it above other ſacrifice, for it is the habitation of his holineſs.</p>
               <p>Finally, The benefits that attend ſuch as give Chriſts ſervants their due encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. If I may take leave once again to look back into the Old Teſtament Mapp, recorded in the Propheſie of <hi>Malaechy,</hi> I will ſhew you a three-fold bleſſing that attends this duty. 1. The Lord invites and tempts them to do
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:173115:85"/>their duty. 2. He is pleaſed to promiſe upon doing their duty, he will pour out bleſſings, and that abundantly for their ſakes. 3. He will remove the curſe, ſtop the deſtroyer, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the conſumer, and rebuke the devourer. 4. The Lord will ſo raiſe their fame and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, that they ſhall be called a bleſſed people, and that by all Nations. In my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of Old Teſtament Scriptures, 'tis not to make it our rule, but to make uſe of their concurrences and aſſiſtances, for they may in ſome meaſure help us as mapps and glaſſes to diſcover our duties, and to ſee our dangers. For as in the Goſpell dayes, duties are more richly and rarely bleſſed, ſo new teſtaments, neglects,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.28, 29.</note> and contempts, are more ſorely and dreadfully puniſht. Thus I have as it were ſet ſome Land-marks to guide you in the way to felicity, and alſo diſcovered ſome Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks to avoid the rocks of miſery; and having thus born my teſtimony, I commend you all to God, and wiſh you eternall manſions of glory.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:173115:86"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>NOw if any Brother or Well-wiſher ſhall conſcientiouſly doubt or be diſ-ſatisfied, touching any particular Point contained in this Treatiſe, becauſe of my ſpeaking to many things in a little room: And if he or they ſhall be ſerious in ſo doing, and will be-friend me ſo far, and do me that courteſie, to ſend to me, before they condemn me, and let me know their ſcruples in a few words of writing, I ſhall look upon my ſelf obliged both in affection and reaſon, to endeavour to give them full ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:173115:86"/>
            <head>A Table of the principall Matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Book.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CHAP. I. THe Cauſes of peace and proſperity in the Churches of Jeſus Chriſt. page 1, 2.</item>
               <item>The antiquity and dignity of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. p. 3.</item>
               <item>The perſonall and princely Excellencies in Chriſt, as the head of his Church. p. 6.</item>
               <item>Chap. 2. Shewing the definition of Church-Government in New Teſtament dayes, <hi>viz.</hi> in not inflicting bodily puniſhment upon of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders, but ſpiritually executing Laws without knowing faces, reſpecting perſons, wreſting cauſes, either for favour or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to any perſons. p. 9.</item>
               <item>A true Miniſters moſt ſpeciall work and duty to the flock under all circumſtances, laid down. p. 11, 12.</item>
               <item>Chap. 3. Shewing the neceſſity of and reaſons for Church-Governours and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. p. 12, 13.</item>
               <item>Chap. 4. Shewing the good uſe and great benefit that comes by right Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. p. 19.</item>
               <item>Right Government is deſtructive to iniquity,
<pb facs="tcp:173115:87"/>and a protection to piety. p. 22, 23.</item>
               <item>Chap. 5. Rules tendred to accompliſh a right Government, and the manner how to chooſe their Officers. p. 26. 27.</item>
               <item>The work of the Officers when choſen. p. 28, 29, 30.</item>
               <item>Chap. 6. Shewing the duty of Chriſtians, as they ſtand related to civill Magiſtrates, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring civill ſubjection, not only for wrath, but for conſcience ſake. p. 38.</item>
               <item>Chap. 7. Treating of Family duties, Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours to Inferiours, and Inferiours to Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, with Directions to a religious choice in Yoke-fellows. p. 40, 41, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Chap. 8. Treating particularly of Family du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. p. 51.</item>
               <item>Chap. 9. Treating of private and perſonall Government. p. 56.</item>
               <item>Cautions not to grieve Gods Spirit, nor offend Conſcience. p. 61.</item>
               <item>Rules for the heart, mouth, eyes, and ears. p. 65, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Chap. 10. Shewing the true order and right manner of executing Church-Government, in ſeven Rules. p. 73, 74.</item>
               <item>Chap. 11. Treating of reſtitution to be made by an offender. p. 76.</item>
               <item>Concerning dealing with Hereticks, and other offenders. p. 77, 78.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:173115:87"/>
               <item>Chap. 12. Rules of Diſcipline how to treat an offender in orderlyeſt wayes; how to reſtore him. p. 80.</item>
               <item>Rules of better obſervation of the Lords Day, or Firſt Day Sabbath. p. 83.</item>
               <item>Rules for Admonition of penitent perſons after Excommunication. p. 87.</item>
               <item>Chap. 13. Shewing what Priviledges are to be maintained to Officers, and Members in Chriſts Congregation. p. 88, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Chap. 14. Shewing what Diſorders ought to be prevented, corrected, or removed. p. 95.</item>
               <item>Rules how the offended ought to treat the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending Brother. p. 97, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Seven Deſcriptions of the nature of the Devil, the Churches adverſary, by his names. p. 102.</item>
               <item>Chap. 15. Shewing what Branches of injuſtice and oppreſſion are to be avoided in the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment of ſin. p. 103.</item>
               <item>Chap. 16. Shewing the true order and the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Diſcipline and Juſtice. p. 105.</item>
               <item>Rules to ſet out the ugly nature of ſin in its ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations, to the thorow humbling the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender. p. 109.</item>
               <item>Uſefull Directions for the promoting and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving unity and peace in the Churches of Chriſt. p. 112, 113, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Chap. 17. Giving Directions how to uphold
<pb facs="tcp:173115:88"/>and preſerve Church-Government. p. 115 &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Chap. 18. Shewing the duty of particular El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders over particular Churches. p. 119. to 124.</item>
               <item>Chap. 19. Shewing the Office and Duty of Deacons in Chriſts Congregations. p. 124. to 129.</item>
               <item>Chap. 20. Shewing the Duty of Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to their Officers. p. 129, 130, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>A Duty incumbent and of high concern for Churches to preſent humble, frequent, and fervent prayers, for ſuch as are called to be Goſpell-Governours, that they may rule for God in juſtice and righteouſneſs, and for the encreaſe of faithfull Labourers in his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt. p. 132, to 135.</item>
               <item>Chap. 21. Shewing what God hath ordained reſpecting his Miniſters Maintenance. p. 135, 136, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>The Neceſſity of making carefull and ſutable proviſion for the Miniſtry, with the ſad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects that accompany the contrary. p. 139, 140, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Encouragements to this work, ſhewing the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that attend the due performance of it. p. 143, 144, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>Counſell to forwardneſs in aſſiſting the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry with our worldly poſſeſſions: Alſo a
<pb facs="tcp:173115:88"/>Caution againſt Covetonſneſs, deſcribing what it is. p. 145, 146.</item>
               <item>Objections againſt this needfull work anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. p. 148.</item>
               <item>A generall reſolution in all difficult and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Caſes. p. 149.</item>
               <item>The dreadfull conſequences in Miniſter and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to do the work of the Lord negligently, with comfortable Encouragements to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant diligence. p. 150, 151, 152, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
